<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The last East-Indian voyage Containing much varietie of the state of the seuerall kingdomes where they haue traded: with the letters of three seuerall Kings to the Kings Maiestie of England, begun by one of the voyage: since continued out of the faithfull obseruations of them that are come home.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 43 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69259</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S111992</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847251</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847251</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12277</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69259)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12277)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 218:21, 1523:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The last East-Indian voyage Containing much varietie of the state of the seuerall kingdomes where they haue traded: with the letters of three seuerall Kings to the Kings Maiestie of England, begun by one of the voyage: since continued out of the faithfull obseruations of them that are come home.</title>
                  <author>Middleton, Henry, Sir, 1570-1613, attrib. name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[76] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. P[urfoot] for Walter Burre,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Sir Henry Middleton--MiU.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-K⁴.</note>
                  <note>Formerly also STC 17869.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reels 218 identified as STC 7456 and 1523 identified as STC 17869.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>East India Company. --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12277:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12277:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:12277:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12277:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Laſt Eaſt-Indian Voyage.</p>
            <p>CONTAINING MVCH varietie of the State of the ſeuerall kingdomes where they haue traded: <hi>with the Letters of three ſeuerall Kings to the Kings Maiestie of England,</hi> begun by one of the Voyage: ſince continued out of the faithfull obſeruations of them that are come home. (⸪)</p>
            <p>AT LONDON, Printed by <hi>T. P.</hi> for <hi>Walter Burre.</hi> 1606.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12277:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12277:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe beginner of this relation following, would no doubt if he had liued haue himſelfe ſet it out to thy good liking: but this I aſſure thee, that both his &amp; this continuation of it is ſet forth with as much faithfulnes as could be gathered out of the beſt obſeruations of them that are come home. If I find it to thy liking, looke ſhortly for an exact and large diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe written by Maiſter Scot chiefe factor or at <hi>Bantam,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer ſince the firſt voyage, containing whatſoeuer hath happe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſince their firſt Arriuall there to trade in thoſe parts reade this, looke for the other, and ſoe farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>VV. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:12277:4"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12277:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>THE LAST EAST INDIAN VOYAGE.</head>
            <head type="sub">Containing many memorable <hi>mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the ſtate of the Countreys where they haue traded. March the 23. 1603/4.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eing prouided of all thinges ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie for ſo long a Voyage, with leaue taken of the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, and others of the Commi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, wee departed from <hi>Graueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end</hi> the 25. of March, being Sunday at night, and the tueſday following came to the Downes, where the Generall before wee came to an anchor, gaue order to the Purſer to call the company, and take their names: which being done, there was found 40 men lacking of the copelment of our Ship, ſo that wee were forced thereby to come to anchor, to tarrie for them. The Generall gaue order preſently the Pinneſſe ſhould be man'd, and ſent the Maſter with his brother, and the Purſer for better diſpatch to <hi>Sandwich,</hi> where they eſcaped verie neere drowning. The Aſſention Pinneſſe likewiſe put off to ſet their Pilate a land, and ſo was caſt away: which when the Generall heard of, he
<pb facs="tcp:12277:5"/>was exceeding angry with Captaine <hi>Stiles</hi> that hee would offer to go a land at ſuch a time without his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. The laſt of March the Maſter, Captaine <hi>Middle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> and the maſters Mate came aboord. The firſt of Aprill, we weighed anchor in the Downes and twarth <hi>Douer,</hi> we found our men in Ketches readie to come aboord, wee tooke them all into our ſhippe, being 28 men, which was farr ſhort of that number wee expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. But howſoeuer the Generall was determined to proceede, although hee lacked fortie men, rather than looſe the benefite of ſo faire a winde: ſo the ſame day of Beachey, the Generall gaue order to the Boatſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwayne to take new muſter of our men; and he found wee had twentie more than our copelment aboord the Admirall, and trarrying to ſpeake with the reſt of the ſhips, wee hal'd them one after another, and found they had euerie ſhip more than their copelment; the cauſe of which errour, could not bee imagined with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out fowle weather cauſed them to hide themſelues, at ſuch time of generall muſter; or elſe that ſome of them miſdoubting they ſhould be ſet on land, played leaſt in ſight: but howſoeuer, this ouer-plus of men was as grieuous to the Generall as the lacke he had afore. To ſee how he had been deluded to come to anchor with a faire wind for lacke of men, and now of force muſt put into ſome place to ſet them againe a land. So the Generall gaue order to the Maſter, hee ſhould haue a care he did not paſſe <hi>Plimouth</hi> that night, for that hee was minded to put in there to diſcharge thoſe men. So the next day morning at day breake, wee were readie with tacks aboord to ſtand into the ſound of <hi>Plimouth:</hi> and ſtood in a good while, till ſuch time as it began to
<pb facs="tcp:12277:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>be guſtie weather. And the wind to ſouther vpon vs, ſo that we were enforced againſt the Generals liking, to proceed on our Voyage ſteering alongſt the land with much winde, and in the afternoone we loſt ſight of <hi>England;</hi> and ſo continuing our courſe with a faire wind, vpon thurſday being the 6. day of Aprill, wee were twarth Cape <hi>Fenneſter,</hi> and the 7 day, of the <hi>Rocke.</hi> And vpon Eaſter day being the 8 day, of Cape Saint <hi>Vincences</hi> with the wind large, and faire weather; and continuing our courſe till the 15, wee came to the <hi>Canaries,</hi> where in the calmes, triall was made to take in the Hectors boat, but ſhee could not ſtoe her, by reaſon ſhe was both too long, and too broad, which if ſhe could haue done, the Generall was minded not to touch in any place til he doubled the Cape: ſo that was the principall cauſe he went to the Iſlands of <hi>Cape-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerde,</hi> ſo the ſame night wee departed from the <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> and directed our courſe for <hi>Maio,</hi> one of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayd Iſlands.</p>
            <p>The 22. day, we had ſight of <hi>Boa Viſta:</hi> the 24. day we anchored at <hi>Maio</hi> vpon the ſouth weſt ſide, where the Generall with the reſt of the Captaines and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants went a land to ſeeke freſh water: but there was none to be found but a ſmall Well, which would yeeld ſcarſe a Hogſ-head a day. Preſently after our landing, there came to our General a <hi>Portingale</hi> that had woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded one of his fellowes, deſiring to ſaue his life, and vpon that conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he would giue him al the welth he had, which was ſome 500, dryed Goats. 7 he Generall would giue no eare to him nor his requeſt, for that he would giue no occaſion of offence, to them of the Iſland, yet by intreaty of the Viſe admirall &amp; the other
<pb facs="tcp:12277:6"/>captaines he was contented to take his Goats and him aboard, which preſently was effected; alſo the ſame after-noone, there came two <hi>Portingales</hi> more of the Iſland to our Generall, who came verie kindly vnto him and bad him welcome, ſo after ſome diſcourſe the Generall deſired them that for his money, he might buy ſome liue goats of them for the refreſhing of his men, they preſently made anſwere againe, they would ſell none but that we might kill as many as wee would, and no bodie would be offended thereat, and ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently they went with the Generall, and ſhewed him how we ſhould encloſe them, and ſo ſet our dogs vpon them; and hauing killed halfe a dozen of goats, they tooke their leaue in friendly maner for that night, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing in the morning to returne and bring their dogs with them, and to helpe vs to ſo many Goats as wee would deſire, ſo the Generall with all the reſt came preſently a board.</p>
            <p>The next day, the Generall would not goe a land, but ſent Captaine <hi>Stiles,</hi> Captaine <hi>Keeling,</hi> and Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Middleton,</hi> with expreſſe order to keepe their people from ſtraggling, and when all their companie were landed, Captaine <hi>Stiles</hi> called them all together; giueing them warning to keepe companie together, and not range one from the other, which ſpeech was reitterated againe by Maiſter <hi>Durham</hi> ſaying, that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer was found ſtraggling, ſhould be ſeuerely puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and therefore willed them all to take good heed. And ſo after this warning giuen, they marched vp into the countrie to kill ſome Goates, where they met with two <hi>Portugals,</hi> which did as ſift them in all the might: in the meane while they were at their ſport a land, The
<pb facs="tcp:12277:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Generall with thereſt, were buſie in ſlowing the Hee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors long boot, for that he was minded, to goe to Sea ſo ſoone as they had done, but they could not ſtowe her; without cutting of her ſtem: &amp; part of her bowes, which ſeeing no other way, was preſentlie efected. And ſo drawing toward night, our land men repaired aboorde, with ſome few Goates they had killed. And after ſupper the wind comming of the land, the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall gaue order to the Maiſter to wey, and that a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning peece might be ſhot of. And ſo preſently the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble was brought to capſtaine and our ſhippe was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently looſe, but before we had vp our anker, Captaine <hi>Stiles</hi> ſent word one of their Marchants was misſing ſo that wee came preſently to Anker againe, and did ride tell day. Hee that loſt himſelfe, was the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie which was ſo carefull to giue other men war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which tooke none himſelfe. Day no ſooner ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing, but the Generall ſent Captaine <hi>Stiles</hi> with at leaſt 150. men to ſeeke for him. And if it were posſible to ſpeake with ſome of the <hi>Portugals:</hi> but all that day was ſpent in vaine, and no news of him; ſo the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall would ſpend no longer time there, but left him to learne the language: ſo the 16. of <hi>May</hi> wee paſſed the line where many of our men fell ſicke of the Scuruy, Calenture, Bloudy flix, and the Wormes, being left to the mercie of God, and a ſmale quantitie of Lyman iuyce euery morning: our phiſition ſhipt for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe being as vnwilling as ignorant in any thing that might helpe them. A great ouerſight in the compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and no doubt wilbe better lookt to hereafter.</p>
            <p>And to our proceeding voyage the 13. day of <hi>Iuly</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Friday we had ſight of Cape, Bona, <hi>Eſperanſa,</hi> the
<pb facs="tcp:12277:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>wind at South-weſt, a gentell gale the Generall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded the tackes a boord intending to go about the cape. But our ſick men cryed out moſt lamentably, for at that preſent there were ſicke of the ſcuruy at the leaſt 80. men in our ſhip, not one able to helpe the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, who made a petition to the Generall moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly entreating him for Gods ſake to ſaue there liues, and to put in for <hi>Saldania</hi> other wayes they were but dead men. The Generall peruſing there pitifull com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint, and looking out of his cabin dore, where did attend a ſwarme of lame and weake diſeaſed criples, who behoulding this lamentable ſight, extended his compaſion towards them. And graunted their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts: that night the wind came vp at the South and continued tell the 17. day before we could get into the rode. The next morning being Wedneſday the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall went on land, with prouiſion to ſet vp tents, &amp; a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle way from our landing place, the <hi>Negroes</hi> had their houſes: which were no other then a few croked ſticks ſet in the grownd, and mattes caſt ouer them, and they had great ſtore of Cattell, both beeves and ſheepe graſing faire by them. Our Generall and the captains went to batter with them for ſmall peeces of Iron, and bought ſome 12. ſheep, and more would haue ſold vs, till that they ſaw vs begin to ſet vp our tents, which as it ſeemed, was to their diſliking; for that incontinent they pulled downe their houſes, and made them faſt vpon their Beaſts backes, and did driue away; yet all meanes poſsible was ſought to drawe them to ſell vs more: but in no caſe they would abide any lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger with vs, but droue away with all the ſpeed they might. It lay in the generals power to haue taken them all from
<pb facs="tcp:12277:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>them, as ſome counſelled him to doe, but he in no caſe would giue eare therevnto; but let them depart, not doubting but that they would returne againe, ſeeing we offered them no wrong, when it was in our pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to diſpoſſeſſe them of all their cattell. The 19. day we got our ſicke men on land, and the 20. our boats were ſent to the Iſland, where wee found ſuch infinite number of ſeales, that it was admirable to behold, all the ſea-ſhore lyes ouer-ſpread with them, ſome ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping, ſome trauelling into the Iſland, and ſome to the ſea-ward: Beſides all the Rockes which lie a prettie diſtance off ſo full as they can hold, thouſands at a time going, and as many comming out: there bee many of them as bigge as any Beare, and as terrible to behold. And vp towards the middle of the Iſland, there be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite numbers of fowles called <hi>Pengwines, Pellicans,</hi> and <hi>Cormerants,</hi> The <hi>Pengwines</hi> bee as bigge as our greateſt Capons wee haue in England, they haue no winges nor cannot flye, but you may driue them by thouſands in a flocke whether you will, they bee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding fatte, but their fleſh is verie ranke, for that they liue vppon fiſh, there bee ſo many of them vpon this ſmall Iſland, which is not aboue 5. miles about, to lade a ſhippe of 50 tonnes with all. Vpon Sunday the 23 the firſt man that died out of our ſhip. Vpon mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day morning the Generall went into the Countrey to buy freſh victuals, but the people of the countrey ſeeing ſo many in company fled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But the General cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed all the company to make a ſtand, and then ſent 4. to them with a bottell of wine, and victuals, with a Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and a Pipe, they ſeeing no more in company came to them, and did eate, drinke, and daunce with
<pb facs="tcp:12277:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>them ſo they ſeeing with what kindes they were vſed, tooke hart vnto them and came along withour Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to our tents, where they had many toyes beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vpon them. As pins, points, beads, and branches, &amp; ſo they returned all very well pleaſed making ſignes to returne the next day with Cattell, but foule wether preuented them for 3 dayes. The forth day after being the 26. they brought vs 44. ſheepe, and the next day 23, ſheep and two kine, and the next day 15. ſheepe and one bullocke, and the 30 day we bought 120. ſheepe and 6. Beeves, the next day 9. ſheepe and three beeves, and the 2. of Auguſt 3. ſheepe. The 3. of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt: the Generall went in his pinnes and other boats with him to kill whales, for all the bay is full of them, they ſtroke diuers with harping Irons, and eſpecially they in the Suſans pinnes ſtroake their har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping Iron into one of them very ſure, and veered their boate a good ſcope from her, ſhee feeling her ſelfe wounded, towed the boat for the ſpace of halfe an hower, vp and downe the bay, with ſuch ſwiftneſſe that the men were faine to go all of them and ſit in the ſtarne, and let the whale towe them, which was with ſuch ſwiftnes that ſhe ſeemed to flie, but in the end they were Inforced to cut their rope, to keepe their boat from ſincking, they were caried ſo ſwiftly throw the Sea. The next that ſtroak one, was in the Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals pinnes, and there were two of them together, and their fortune was to ſtrike a young one, which plaied like reakes, as the firſt did, and continued for a good time and then they hal'd vp the boat ſomewhat neere, and wounded her in diuers places with iauellins, the great whale all this time would not depart from the
<pb facs="tcp:12277:8"/>little one although it had receiued many wounds, but ſtood to the laſt to fight it out againſt al our boats, ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times giuing one boat a blow, and ſometimes another, and would come vnder our boats, and lift them almoſt out of the water, ſhe beſtowed one bange on the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals Pinneſſe, that ſplit all the timbers and boards, ſo that he was faine to take another boat to ſaue himſelfe; for ſhe was preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly full of water, yet with much a doe they ſaued the Pinneſſe, &amp; brought her on land, where it coſt all our Carpenters three dayes worke to repaire her. And when the young Whale began to be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, the old one would take the young vpon his backe and carrie him, but the old one ſeeing that would not preuaile againſt vs, would leaue his carriage, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take himſelfe to his fight, which was to caſt his tayle out of the water, and to ſtrike ſo valiantly, that if hee had taken any of our boats with one of theſe blowes, he would haue ſplit it all to peeces. It was verie good ſport to ſtand and looke on, but verie dangerous to them in the boats: To conclude of this matter, the young Whale could not be killed till the ſunne-ſet, the old one neuer forſaking her whilſt it had any life. So after it was dead, wee towed it to our landing place, and at hye water hal'd it ſo hye as we could. The oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion why we killed this Whale, was for lacke of oyle for our lampes, for in all the ſhipps we had great lacke, the oyle was put in verie bad caske, and leaked out. But whereas wee hoped to haue had oyle inough out of this Whale to haue ſerued all our turnes, it did ſcarce yeeld foure gallons it was ſo young and leane.</p>
            <p>The 8 day, the Generall ſent a dozen of our men to buy freſh victuals, for that wee had not any left.
<pb facs="tcp:12277:9"/>So they were out all day, and brought home but two ſheepe at their returne, which was late, the Generall demaunded of the Purſer of the Hector, which was cheefe purueyer, what was the occaſion they ſtayed out ſo long, and that they brought no more cattell. He anſwered, that the people had ſould them good ſtore of cattell, which hee had payd for, but being ſo fewe of our men in companie, and they weaponleſſe, they would abuſe them in ſnatching their yron from them, and not to ſuffer them to driue the cattell away they payd for. The Generall ſeeing how they vſed him, thought by policie to goe beyond them; and this it was: Hee himſelfe with 120 men in his companie; would goe by night and lye in ambuſh in a wood nere the place where our men did barter with them, and when it was faire day, the purueyor and his crewe, ſhould come as other times, and bargaine with them for ſo many as they would ſell; And when they had ſufficient to make a ſigne, and then the Generall and his companye ſhould come out of their lodgings, and driue them away. This matter was put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe this night, and the Cenerall three houres before day departed from the tents, and had imbosked him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and all his followers to their owne contents, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly three fellowes of captaine <hi>Stiles</hi> his companie, to taſt of a bottell of wine they caried for their captaine, and in the meane while they were drinking, they had loſt ſight of their <hi>Generall</hi> and all his company and took a contrary way, neuer ſtaying til they came to the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the <hi>Negroes:</hi> they ſeeing three men armed to come to their houſes, began to ſuſpect ſome falſe meaſures; theſe fellowes ſeeing they had miſtaken themſelues,
<pb facs="tcp:12277:9"/>retired backe to the woods, and in ſight of the <hi>Indians</hi> hid themſelues in the buſhes, at that time the Sunne being vp halfe an houre after theſe fellowes had hid themſelues, came our weaponleſſe Merchants from the tents and beganne to barter with them, for two or three ſheepe, which of purpoſe they had ſent downe to our people, to keepe them buſie while they were getting their heards of Cattell to runne away. Which our merchants perceiuing, they preſently vnarmed as they were, went amongſt them, and ſent worde by one of them to the Generall, to come away with all his people; for that he and all his companie were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couered, ſo that the Generall was enforced to breake out of his ambuſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to reſcew his men, which were amongſt them without weapons: but before he could come to their reſcew, they had wounded one of our men, with foure dartes ſticking in his body; which being downe done, they betooke them to their heeles and al the cattel before them, as faſt as they could driue to the mountaines. Our men, as then, hauing the raines in their owne handes, purſued after them in ſuch ſcattering maner, that if the people of the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey had been men of any reſolution, they might haue cut off moſt of them. The Generall cauſed a trumpet to ſound a retreat, but could not cauſe them to leaue their chaſe. And whileſt that he was taking order to ſend the hurt man to the tents, he was halfe a mile from the neereſt of our men, and not paſt fiue men in his company: ſo hee and thoſe men in his company were faine to runne to ouer take ſome of them which were before, that in the end they were a dozen in his
<pb facs="tcp:12277:10"/>company. Yet the Generall tooke it greeuous, to ſee his men ſcatterred ouer all the Playne, &amp; ſcarce three of them together in a company: which if the people of the countrey had ioyned together, and ſet vpon them beeing ſo ſcattered, they had cut moſt of them off, which thing the Generall greatly doubted, yet God be thanked it ſorted better. For ſome of our men ouer-tooke ſome of the <hi>Negroes</hi> at the foote of the mountaine, and draue them away from ſome of their Catttle, and made a ſtand by them till more of their company came vp, and ſo retorned homwardes with a hundred Kyne and Calues, which was wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come to our ſicke men.</p>
            <p>But in our abſence from our Tentes, Captaine <hi>Colthurst,</hi> with the Maſter, and ſuch as were left, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing very doubtfull all was not well with vs, thought it beſt to ſend our Pinneſſe to the bottome of the Baye, to helpe vs if we ſtood in need: but maſter <hi>Cole,</hi> being ouer-bold in his pinneſſe to goe a ſhore, both hee and the boat were caſt away, and two more that preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of their ſwimming were drowned, the reſt eſca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped very hardly, came running naked along the ſands to vs wardes, and there certyfied the Generall of all that happened, which was but forrowfull newes to him. The next day, the Generall ſent ſufficient ſtore of men to march by land, to the place where the boat was caſt away, and found her dry vpon the ſtrand, ſplit and full of ſand: but with much trouble ſhe was freed, and ſent aboord. Alſo we found maſter <hi>Cole</hi> vpon the ſtrand, and brought him to our Tentes, and buryed him.</p>
            <p>This night, and the next after, our ſentenels had
<pb facs="tcp:12277:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſpied the cuntrey people lurking about our rents, ſo that alarome was giuen, and they fled: vpon the 14. of Auguſt we departed all a board our ſhips, where we ridde tell the 19. the wind not ſeruing to carry vs out, which then ſerued our turnes, we put to Sea and ſtood to the Weſtwards, and the 25. day we dubled the cape of <hi>Good hôpe;</hi> with very fauourable windes tell the fift of <hi>September;</hi> and after that time we met with the wind ſcarſe, and now and then calmes, and here began the ſcuruy to grow amongſt our men, and euery day did the diſeaſe encreaſe. Here might ſome what be ſaid of the ignorance and vncharitablenes of him that was ſhipt for our phiſition, as a caueat to them that ſhall go hereafter to be better prouided: but for 2. reſpects I forbear, the one in regard of his other calling but chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for that he is ſince dead in the voyage; where for my part I wiſh his faults may be buried with him.</p>
            <p>The 19. of <hi>December,</hi> we had ſight of <hi>Ingana</hi> an Iland lying neere <hi>Sumatra,</hi> the 20. we had ſight of <hi>Sumatra,</hi> the 21. we ankerd within the Ilands where we were put to great trouble to haue vp our yardes, and get vp our ankors, our men were exceeding weak, we were faine to ſend men out of our ſhip to helpe the reſt, and ſo with much a doe we came to <hi>Bantam</hi> rode. The occaſion why we firſt ankered was becauſe the Aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſhot off a peece of ordenance within night, which was contrarie to our articles, we doubting ſhe was in ſome great diſtreſſe came ſuddenly to an anker to tarie to know what was the matter, which prooued to bee nothing but that there Gunner was dead and throwne ouer board, and had that peece for a farewell: which folly of theirs, put vs to great trouble, cauſing vs to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker
<pb facs="tcp:12277:11"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12277:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12277:12"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12277:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12277:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>in the Sea, in 25. fadomes: then windes all weſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye, which brought in a great ſeagate, that the next day morning, we had much a doe to get vp our anker, and as for the other ſhips they were not able to wey without our helpes, which we ſent them, and ſo with very much trouble, we got vs all vnder ſayle, ſteering away <hi>Eaſt</hi> and by <hi>North,</hi> and <hi>Eaſt North Eaſt,</hi> tell wee came to anker between the Iland and the maine at the entrance of <hi>Bantam</hi> bay, in 7. fadomes ſandy ground. This night at 7. a clock came a Hollands boat a board vs from <hi>Bantam,</hi> ſent by a Generall of 12. ſhips, which came there two dayes before vs; in which boat came the viſe admeral of the fleet, with refreſhing fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhore preſenting it to our Generall, with offer of any kindnes they could doe vs, which afterwards they effected towards vs, in ſending their boats to ſetch vs water: many other curtiſyes beſides, we of our ſelues not able to doe the ſame, our weaknes being ſo great. This fleet had paſſed, along the coſt, from Moſimbique to Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, and had taken diuers ſhips, and burned a Carrick, and afterwards came hither withall their men in good health. An howre after their comming a board of the hollanders came a prawe or a canow from <hi>Bantam,</hi> with maſter Scot &amp; others of our men left their the laſt voyage by whome the Generall knew the eſtate of their buſines, the 23. at 2. a clock we came to anker in <hi>Bantam</hi> rode, and ſaluted the towne and Hollanders with moſt of our ordinance, and were anſwered again with the like from all the Hollanders, the 24. day our viſe-admerall was ſent vnto the king, to excuſe the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals not comming a land, for that he was not well. This day being the 24. came in 2 ſaile of hollands fleet
<pb facs="tcp:12277:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>a ſhippe and a pinnes the ſame day one of the theeus that had ſet our houſe on fire was ſtopped to death. According to the order of the countrey. The 26 day the General gaue new articles to all the ſhips, wherein euery man was abſolutely forbidden to buy any ſpice, and diuers other articles for the good demenor of his men which here I omit to write: The 27. 28. &amp; the 29 nothing happened worth writing. The 30. day the Generall of the Hollanders and moſt part of the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall of his fleet dinied a board with our Generall. The 31. our Generall went on land, with a letter from our Kings Maieſtie, and a preſent to the King of <hi>Bantame</hi> which he deliuered him, and were very acceptably receiued. The King but 13. yeares of age and gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by a protector, the 3. day we had order to ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mage our hould to take prouition of water and marchants goods, for that we were appoynted, &amp; the <hi>Aſſensſion</hi> to go for the molucas, &amp; the other ſhips to take in their lading of peper, and to go home; likewiſe this day we tooke in diuers fardells of Marchandize, and ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued taking in water and Marchandize tell the 8. day, and then our Generall came a board, and appoynted ſuch men as ſhould go a long with him to the molucas amongſt which number, maſter <hi>Tauerner</hi> was remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, from the <hi>Suſan</hi> to the <hi>Aſſensſion,</hi> we continued buſie in taking in of Marchandize, and vittelles of the <hi>Hector</hi> and the <hi>Suſan</hi> tell the 15. day we made an end, of taking in of marchandize. This day our purſſer <hi>William Griffen,</hi> and maſter <hi>Foſter</hi> dyed both of the flixe.</p>
            <p>The ſixteenth day our Cenerall, departed from <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam:</hi> and came a bord to proceed on his voyage to the
<pb facs="tcp:12277:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Mollocos,</hi> this night dyed <hi>Henry Dewbrey</hi> of the Flixe; alſo the ſame day, maiſter <hi>Sur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>flict</hi> was appointed to goe home in the <hi>Hector,</hi> to the great contenting of all in our ſhip: likewiſe one of our maiſters mattes, mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Smith,</hi> was appointed for Maiſters Mate in the <hi>Hector.</hi> The 17. day dyed of the Flixe, <hi>William Lewed, Iohn Ienkens,</hi> and <hi>Samuel Porter</hi> the 18 day the Generall hauing diſpatched his letters, went aboard the <hi>Hector</hi> and the <hi>Suſan</hi> and tooke leaue of them: and after di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner wayed, and ſtood to the ſea-ward till night, and then ankred in 8. fadomes of water the 19. in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning we weyed againe, and proceeded with a faire wind till 6, a clocke at night, &amp; then came to anker in 14. fadome of ye grounde faire by a ſmall Iland; the 20. by breake of day we weyed &amp; ſteering along the land with a faire winde: this day dyed <hi>Henry Stiles</hi> our M. Carpenter, and <hi>Iames Varnam;</hi> and <hi>Iohn Iberſon,</hi> all of the Flix. The 21 and 22 dayes we held on our courſe, with bluſting rainie weather; the 22. day dyed of the Flixe <hi>Iames Hope:</hi> the 24. day in the morning wee fell with the ſhouldes which lye off the Eaſt, North eaſt part of <hi>Iaua:</hi> this day dyed <hi>Iohn Leay,</hi> and <hi>Robert whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> of the Flixe. <hi>Ianuarie</hi> the 25. wee held on our courſe, with very much winde and raine, at night one of our men leaped ouer-board, hauing the <hi>Callenture.</hi> and three more dyed of the Flixe, their names were <hi>William Bellidine, William Pooter, Gedyon Marten,</hi> and <hi>Robert Vennes:</hi> the 26. day ſtering our courſe with a faire wind ſuſpecting no danger, vpon a ſodaine wee ſaw the ground vnder the ſhip, heauing ouer the lead, wee had but 4 fadoms water: this night dyed of the Flixe <hi>George Iohnes,</hi> and <hi>Frances Buck-man,</hi> and <hi>Gilbert
<pb facs="tcp:12277:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>Meſterſon:</hi> the 27. day in the morning wee ſtered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way Eaſt and by South, wee came into ſhould water which lyeth to the ſouth-ward of <hi>Ruinata:</hi> ſo that we were faine to ſtand South and by Weſt and South to get cleare of the ſhouldes till noone, and then wee came into deepe water, and ſo bearing vp we ſtered Eſt and by ſouth and by &amp; by we were in fine fadomes ſo that we ſtood to the ſouth-ward ſome three leages, and then held on our former courſe: this day dyed of the Flixe, <hi>Robert Smith,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Dawſon:</hi> the <hi>28,</hi> day we fell with <hi>Selebis,</hi> being high land, and at 4. a clocke in the euening we came to an anchor in <hi>26.</hi> fadome; ſandy ground, foure leages from land: the <hi>29.</hi> in the morning we weyed, ſteering Eſt along the land, and the Generall went in our pinneſſe alongſt the land to ſeek for freſh water, for that he greatly doubted it was the <hi>Bantam</hi> water that killed our men, but hee loſt his labour, and returned without any for there was none to be found; at night we ankered in 30. fadomes wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, this morning dyed <hi>William Paret</hi> of the flixe: the 30. day we paſſed the ſtraites of <hi>Selibis</hi> and ſhaped our courſe for the Iles of <hi>Beton:</hi> the 31. in the morning we were faire by the land of <hi>Betton,</hi> and all the night lay by the Lee. The firſt of <hi>Februarie</hi> we held on our courſe with a faire winde. the ſecond dyed of the flixe <hi>Henry Lambert:</hi> the third day dyed of the flixe <hi>Edward Smith,</hi> the 4. in the morning we had ſight of <hi>Blewe,</hi> and <hi>Barrow,</hi> being two Hands: this day dyed <hi>Henry Iames,</hi> the fifth day <hi>Richard Miller</hi> dyed of the Flixe: the ſixt day we were faire by the land <hi>Blewe,</hi> and our Generall went in the pinneſſe to ſeeke for freſh water, and went with the people of the Countrey, and they
<pb facs="tcp:12277:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>brought him to a fine ſandy Bay, where there was ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good water; and there they tooke in three Baricoes and brought aboard, and would ſpend no longer time there becauſe it was towardes night, and <hi>Amboyna</hi> ſo neere at hand: the ſeuenth day wee had ſight of <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boyna,</hi> and of a ſhip which played off and on the land, but would not come and ſpeake with vs: this after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone we were faire by <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and the winde very variable but it fell calme, ſo that wee could not get in: the eight day at ten a clocke came vp a gale of winde, which brought vs to <hi>Amboyna</hi> ſhoare, where we coſted with our ſhip very nere, but could not haue any grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to anker in, for that all the Ilands haue very deepe water hard aboard the ſhoare: wee came to a Bay, where we found ſixtie fadomes water, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>re we ankered, and the <hi>Indiaus</hi> brought vs ſome fruits to ſell: this after-noone we ſawe two <hi>Hollanders</hi> pinniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes vnder the ſhoare of <hi>Verranula,</hi> which came out from vnder the land to ſhowe themſelues to vs, but did returne backe.</p>
            <p>The people of <hi>Verranula</hi> be great enemies to the <hi>Portugals,</hi> and had ſent to <hi>Bantam</hi> to the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring their ayde to expell the <hi>Portugals</hi> out of theſe Ilands; which if they performed, they would become ſubiect to them, and ſell none of their Cloues, to any other Nation but them. This I knew to bee true, for that the parties who were ſent to <hi>Bantam,</hi> I haue often ſpoken withall: this day dyed of the Flixe our Maſter his mate <hi>Thomas Michell.</hi> The ninth day wee water<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red but could not come to the ſpeech of any of the countrey people: this after noone dyed <hi>Thomas El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred</hi> of the Flixe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12277:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The tenth day wee weyed anker, and ſtood to the Eaſter ende of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and came to an anker in an hundred fadomes water, fayre by the ſhoare, fayre by a towne called <hi>Mamalla.</hi> Before we came to an anker, there came an <hi>Indian</hi> aboard of vs which ſpake good Portugeſe, alſo there came a letter to our Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall from the Captaine of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> but it was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to the Generall of the <hi>Hollenders,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Captaine of his fleete, ſuppoſing vs to be <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenders.</hi> 
               <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> The effect of his Letter was, to deſire them to certifie them of ſome newes of <hi>Portingale,</hi> and to ſend an anſwere by any of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of his letter, who ſhould bee verie welcome, and ſhould both ſafely come and goe. The Generall went this day a land, and deliuered a preſent to one they called their King and other great men, and did deſire to know whether wee might haue trade or no: they made anſwere, that they could not trade with vs without licence of the Fort: this night dyed of the flixe <hi>Marke Taylor.</hi> The 11 day our Generall ſent a letter by <hi>Iohn Rogers</hi> to the captaine of the Fort, and diners of the principall of the towne of <hi>Mamalla</hi> accompanied him thether to haue licence to trade with vs, which they had granted them by the captaine: the effect of our Generals letter, was to certifie him of the death of our <hi>Queen,</hi> &amp; peace between <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> with other news of Chriſtendome, &amp; for better confirmatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of truth, he ſent the captain of the ſort, our kings Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fly &amp; the princes pictures, with diuers of his Maieſties new coine, &amp; in concluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as there was peace with our Princes and their ſubiects in Chriſtendome he deſired that the like might be between vs, for that our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming
<pb facs="tcp:12277:16"/>was to ſeeke trade with them and the <hi>Amboynians</hi> which he hoped he would not deny him. The party which caried our <hi>Generals</hi> letter, was very kindly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertained by the Captaine and Souldiers, but that night permitted not him to come within the fort: but lay in a good lodging without the walles, where he was vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeted by the principall of them. This euening 5 ſayles of <hi>Hollanders</hi> were entered into the mouth of the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor and turnning vp for the fort. The 12. the forena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Hollanders</hi> came to an anker within musket ſhot of the fort, the <hi>Portugals</hi> not offering to ſhoote at them, this afternoone <hi>Iohn Rogers</hi> returned with an anſwere of the letter and their came in his company a <hi>Portugall</hi> Souldier, which brought a warrant from the Captaine to the Gouernor of <hi>Manillia,</hi> to trade with vs, and like wiſe to giue <hi>Iohn Rogers</hi> for his pains a <hi>Bahar</hi> of cloues, which was preſently deliuered him, before the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming away of <hi>Iohn Rogers</hi> the <hi>Portugals</hi> with a flagge of truce went a board the dutch Admerall to knowe wherefore they came thither; if in friend ſhippe they ſhould be welcome: if otherwaies to giue them a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect anſwere, the dutch Generall made anſwere that his comming thither was to haue that Caſtell from them, and willed them, to deliuer him the keyes and they ſhould be kindly dealt withall. Which if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to do, he willed them to prouide for themſelues to defend it, for that he was minded to haue it before he departed, and that his ſtaying was but for the reſt of his fleet, which as then were in ſight. Therefore wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led them by faire meanes to yeald, the <hi>Portugals</hi> made anſwere the Caſtell was their Kings, and of ſufficient ſtrength, and therefore willed them to depart thence.
<pb facs="tcp:12277:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>And as he came as a meſſenger in way of truce they deſired they might haue free libertie to depart, which was granted the with an anſwer in writing to the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, willing him to ſurrender vp this fort vnto him in the prince of <hi>Orringe</hi> his name, by 2. a clock that day, or looke for the extremity of warre, what after paſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I know not. The anſwer of our Generals let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from the Captaine of the fort was, that he and all the <hi>Portugals</hi> in the place were exceeding glad of the good news we brought them of that long and wiſhed for peace, betweene our nations and that there was not any thing in their power; In that Iland wherein they might pleaſure vs, but we ſhould commaund it. And as touching the cloues of <hi>Manillia,</hi> he had ſent ſpeciall order to the Gouernor, to make ſale of all they might make, at a reſonable price, and likewiſe he had good ſtore of cloues in his caſtell, which ſhould be all ours if playſed the Generall to come with what ſpeed he could thither, whereby he hoped to Come to ſome good compoſition with the Hollanders. This day dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the flixe <hi>Daniell Aske.</hi> The 13. we wayed our ankers to come ride nearer the ſhore of <hi>Manillia;</hi> but our Generall made the <hi>Portingall</hi> ſouldier beleeue he wayed to go to the fort which was no part of his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, for that there was not any hope of good to be done for vs, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> being there before vs, but before we came to an anker, we hard ordinance goe of, ſo that we made account the fight was begun be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them, for that the <hi>Portingall</hi> ſouldier tould our Generall, they would neuer yeild vp their fort, but fight it out to the laſt man, with many other braggs of their ſtrength and reſolution, which afterwards pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
<pb facs="tcp:12277:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>to be nothing but words. This day our Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall went a land with ſome Marchandize to barter with them, but nothing was donne that day but put of tell the next day.</p>
            <p>The fourteenth our Marchants went a ſhore with commodites, and the chiefe of the towne came and priſed our wares: which they liked very well; But offered very little for them, and for ſuch cloues as they had, they would not ſell vnder 100. ryalls of 8. the ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>har which made ſhoe they had no will to deale with vs: The <hi>Portingall</hi> ſouldier went a land, with our Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall with a letter to his Captaine and foure yards of greene cloth giuen him for a reward, but when they came to talke with the people to know what newes at the fort, ſome ſayd it was taken, others ſaid they were in fight, but in theſe doubts their came a meſſenger from the fort, which brought vs certaine newes, it was yealded to the <hi>Hollanders</hi> by compoſition, but vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on what conditions I knew not. The <hi>Portingall</hi> ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier hearing this certaine newes durſt not returne, for fear the people would cut his throt by the way, but deſired the Generall he might tarry with him, which he granted; and after the Gouernor of the towne, had hard that the Hollanders had the caſtle, He then tould our Generall he would ſell vs no cloues without li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of the Hollanders, ſo that all hope of trade in this place was gone. The fifteenth day we tooke in water, and made particio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the marchandize, to the Aſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for ſhee had taken none in at <hi>Bantam,</hi> but all was put in to our ſhip by reaſon they were ſo exceeding weak, they were no table to ſtoe them.</p>
            <p>Here our Generall was almoſt in deſpaire for the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning
<pb facs="tcp:12277:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>of his layding, and eſpecially for <hi>Cloues, Nut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megs,</hi> and <hi>Mace;</hi> we hard they had good ſtore at <hi>Banda,</hi> but the <hi>Hollanders</hi> were there before vs with great ſtore of ſuch commodities as we had, which they had taken in a ſhip bound to the <hi>Molucos,</hi> laden with the ſame commodities, yet there was hope of the <hi>Banda</hi> commodities which is Nuts and Mace, by reaſon of the great quantie we hard ſay they had: likewiſe this day the Generall called a counſell of the <hi>Captains, Maiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> and <hi>Marchants,</hi> and there told them, that their was no way left vs to attaine to our lading, but to part com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany. And the Aſſention to goe for the Iles of <hi>Banda</hi> to ſeeke her lading of <hi>Nutmegs</hi> and <hi>Mace,</hi> and that he was minded with the <hi>Dragon</hi> to goe to the <hi>Molucas,</hi> or elſe at leaſtwilſe to doe his beſt to get thither.</p>
            <p>This ſpeech of his was diſliked of all: for that in both our Shippes at that preſent were not ſo many ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiceable men as would ſayle the Aſſention, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we ſhould hazard both the ſhips to part company hauing ſo weake a company, and likewiſe to attempt the Voyage to the <hi>Mollucas,</hi> it was againſt reaſon, for that he had both the wind and corrant againſt vs, and to plye it to winde ward with ſo weake a company, it would be loſt labour. This was the opinion of all, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the General, who ſtil had a good hope we ſhould attaine it. At this time nothing was concluded, but left to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidered vpon til the next morning. The 16 day very early in the morning before day, M. <hi>Groue</hi> came to the <hi>Generals</hi> bed ſide, telling him he cold take no reſt all the night, for thinking of the motion made by him, &amp; our going to the <hi>Molucas,</hi> although it was a thing neuer attempted by any, yet he ſaw no other way to put it in
<pb facs="tcp:12277:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>practiſe; otherwiſe we muſt make account to returne backe to <hi>Bantam</hi> without lading.</p>
            <p>The General was glad to heare him of that minde, and at the comming aboord of Captaine <hi>Choulthurſt,</hi> and his maſter, it was abſolutely determined vpon, to part company, although greatly to the diſlike of them both, for they thought neuer to ſee vs again: our weakneſſe in both ſhips being ſo exceeding weake: the ſeuenteenth day wee wayed, and plyed to winde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward all the day and all the night to get to ſea, the way we came in: the eighteenth day we got to ſea cleare of <hi>Amboyna,</hi> and ſtood to ſea till the after-noone, and then wee parted company with the <hi>Aſcention,</hi> bearing vp for <hi>Banda</hi> afore the winde, not hauing paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing a day and a halfe ſaile. From the eighteene to the one and twentie, wee plyed it and got very little to wind-wards; this day it fell calme, and we were cari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed betweene two <hi>Ilandes,</hi> they bee called <hi>Manipa,</hi> and <hi>Ambovzeylioe,</hi> with a great currant, and loſt more in the calme in one night, then we had got in two dayes: the Generall ſent his brother to <hi>Manipa,</hi> to buy freſhe vittels, but euery thing was ſo deare they came with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, ſauing a couple of Goats the king ſent our Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall for a preſent.</p>
            <p>The king of this Ile vſed our men very kindly, and feaſted them, being very glad to heare of the health of our Queene: he asked for Sir <hi>Francis Drake:</hi> this king was at <hi>Tarnata,</hi> when Sir <hi>Fraucis Drake</hi> was there. The two and twentieth day, we ankered vnder <hi>Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa,</hi> on the South weſt ſide, in 50 fadomes: this day dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Thomas Harman</hi> of the Flixe: the three and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth, we weyed with very much adoe, for our anker
<pb facs="tcp:12277:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>was foule of a rock, we broke one of the flooks there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, before we could way it. The 24. day moſt part calme, in which calmes we were caried very neer <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipa</hi> ſhore, all ſayles ſtanding and vpon a ſudden came a guſt, which had like to haue put vs vpon a ledge of rocks, which we had no way to auoyde, but all ſayles ſtanding came to an anker, we ankerd within a quoits caſt of the rocks, and ſo eſcaped that danger. The 25. day died <hi>Thomas Beynes:</hi> the 27. day much raine, the winde weſterly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>March,</hi> the firſt, the windes all Northerly: this day dyed of the Flixe <hi>Thomas Wheeler:</hi> the ſecond day the winde at the North weſt for the moſt part, this day dyed of the flixe, <hi>Richard Hedges;</hi> and <hi>William Flud.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third day we came faire by an Iland, not ſpecified in our cards, it lieth Weſt South weſt, from the Southermoſt Iland of <hi>Bachan</hi> ſome foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene leagues: this Ile of <hi>Bachan,</hi> we gaue to name <hi>Hathowling,</hi> for that in 7. dayes ſailing we got not a mile: the fourth and fift dayes we plied all we might, but could doe noe good, and thoſe few ſound men wee had were tyred with contiuall labour, wee at this preſent lacking both woode and water, came to an anker vnder <hi>Halbowling</hi> in ſixtie fadomes, this time the Maiſter and boatſone were both very ſicke of the flixe, inſomuch that the Generall was in great doubt of their recouery: the ſixt day very much wind, at North weſt, our Generall went a land to ſeeke for freſh water but could find none, but digging a well in the ſand wee founde verye good water, as for Woode, wee needed not to ſeeke for; that the
<pb facs="tcp:12277:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>Iſland yeelded nothing but wood to the ſea-ſide, that one was ſcarce able to paſſe, the trees and brakes were ſo thicke: here our portingal ſouldier was verie ſicke of the flixe, and the Generall was verie carefull of him, for that he hoped by his meanes to haue trade with the <hi>Portingales</hi> of <hi>Tydore</hi> for <hi>Cloues.</hi> The 7.8, and 9 dayes, wee ſpent in wooding and watering, which wee got all aboard: the ninth day the windes continuing northerly with much raine. This day di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of the flixe <hi>William Elmeſmore,</hi> The 10. day wee weyed, but had much adoe to gette vp a ſmall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor, our weakeneſſe was ſo great, that wee could not ſtart it without tackles: this day dyed <hi>Dauid Flud.</hi> The 11. day raynie weather, the winde at north-weſt, wee ſtood to the northeaſt-ward: this day dyed one of our Marchants called Maſter <hi>George Ware</hi> of the flixe. The 12, 13, and 14 dayes, wee ſpent in turning to wind-ward, ſometimes vpon one tacke, ſometimes of the other. The 13. day dyed <hi>Edward Ambroſe</hi> of the flixe. The 15. and 16. dayes, the windes eaſterly, wee made ſome 19. leagues north weſt.</p>
            <p>The 17. day wee were in 10. minutes of ſouth lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, the windes all weſterly, and wee ranne ſome 10. leagues north: this day we had ſight of all the Cloue-Iſlands, that is to ſay, <hi>Makian, Muter, Tidore</hi> and <hi>Tarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> all of them picked hilles in forme of a ſugar-loafe. The 18 and 19 dayes, wee were faire vnder the land of <hi>Makian;</hi> Betweene that and <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>olr,</hi> where the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Makian</hi> came aboard of vs with freſh victuals, but ſould verie deere: they ſayd they had good ſtore of Cloues in the Iſland: but they could not ſell vs any without leaue of the King of <hi>Tarn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> The 20 and 21.
<pb facs="tcp:12277:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>we ſpent plying to winde wards with little wind, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Makian, &amp; Muter.</hi> This Iſland of <hi>Muter</hi> is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inhabited, but hath great ſtore of Cloues vpon it, this Iſland ſtandeth between <hi>Tidor &amp; Makian,</hi> but neerer to <hi>Makian</hi> by one third of the way tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is to <hi>Tidore;</hi> the people of this Iſland haue been ſlaine moſt part in the wars between <hi>Tarnata</hi> and <hi>Tydore,</hi> for ſometime it was ſubiect to one King, and ſometime to another. The 22. day, we got vnder the land of <hi>Tydore,</hi> and bearing vp between a ſmall Iſland called <hi>Pulo Cauallie,</hi> and <hi>Tydor,</hi> there came rowing two of their Galleys from <hi>Tarnata,</hi> making all the ſpeed poſsible they could toward vs, the headmoſt of the two weuing with a white flagge vnto vs to ſtrike ſayle, and to tarrie for them. At the ſame time came 7. <hi>Tydore</hi> Galleys, rowing betwixt vs and the ſhoare, to chaſe the <hi>Turnatanes</hi> Galleys, wee not knowing their pretence, they in the <hi>Tarnate</hi> Galleys did all they might to ouertake our Ship wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing with two or three flags at once to tarie for them, which our Generall ſeeing, cauſed the top-ſayles to be ſtrucke, and lay by the lee to knowe what was the matter; ſo that the formoſt of theſe Galleys or <hi>Cara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colles</hi> recouered our ſhippe, wherein was the King of <hi>Tarnata,</hi> and diuers of his Noble-men, and three Dutch Marchants, when they had faſt hold of the ſhip, the Dutch Marchants ſhewed themſelues to vs loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king pale, and deſired our Generall for Gods ſake, to reſcue the Caracole that came after vs, wherein were diuers <hi>Dutch-men,</hi> which were like to fall into the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies handes, where there was no hope of mercie, but preſent death: wherevpon our Generall cauſed our Gunner to ſhoote at the <hi>Tydore</hi> Galleys, yet
<pb facs="tcp:12277:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>that would not cauſe them to leaue their chace, but within ſhot of our ordinance diſcharged all their ſhot at the <hi>Tarnata</hi> Galley, and preſently boarded them, and put all to the ſword ſauing three men, which ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued their liues by ſwimming, and were taken vp by our men in our boate, there were no <hi>Dutch-men</hi> in her as they reported, but all <hi>Tarnatanes:</hi> if wee had not tarryed as wee did, the King of <hi>Tarnata</hi> and thoſe with him, had fallen into his enemies hand, where no hope of mercle was to bee expected: the Dutch-marchants comming aboard, told our Generall they thought wee had beene <hi>Hollenders,</hi> and bound for <hi>Tarnata,</hi> and that was the cauſe they had put them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues in ſuch danger, and likewiſe to know whether wee were bound, our Generall told them that he was going then for <hi>Tydore,</hi> to ſeeke trade with the <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gals,</hi> with whom we were in amitie: they diſwaded the Generall not to attempt any ſuch thing, for there was no other thing to bee expected at their handes but trecherie; the Generall anſwered hee knew them well enough, but minded to worke ſo warily with them, that hee doubted not of any harme they could doe him.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Dutch-men</hi> ſeeing our Generall minded to goe to the <hi>Portugall-towne</hi> of <hi>Tydore,</hi> deſired him that he would not let the king of <hi>Tarnata</hi> and them fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their enemies hand: whom ſo lately he had deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red them from, &amp; as for Clowes there was good ſtore to bee had at <hi>Tarnata,</hi> and <hi>Makean,</hi> and for their parts they would not bee our hindrance, for that they had nether wares nor money left. So the Generall cauſed
<pb facs="tcp:12277:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>them to entreat the king to come into the ſhip, who came in trembling: which the General ſeeing thought hee was a colde, and cauſed his man to fetch him a blacke damaske gowne, layde with golde lace, and lyned with vnſhorne Veluet, which the king put vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his backe, but neuer had the maners to ſurrender it againe, but kept it as his owne: the king being in the Generals Cabin deſired him to goe with him to <hi>Tarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta,</hi> where hee minded to haue a factorie, but himſelfe and his ſhippe would make no ſtay there, but goe to <hi>Tydore,</hi> to ſee what vſage hee ſhould finde of the <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tugals.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The king did what hee could to perſwade him to the contrary but could not preuayle. Heare the Generall deliuered a Letter from the KINGS MAIESTIE of <hi>ENGLAND,</hi> with a fayre ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Cuppe, and a couer double gilt, with diuers of the choiſeſt <hi>Pintadoes,</hi> which hee kindly accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of, and preſently had the Letter red, and enterpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto him where-with hee made ſhewe to bee greatly contented.</p>
            <p>Wee trimmed our Sailes by a winde, and plyed to winde ward for <hi>Tarnata:</hi> the Kings <hi>Carracole</hi> not daring to put from the ſhippe. About foure of the clocke in the after-noone, came the King of <hi>Tarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas</hi> eldeſt ſonne aboard in a light Frigat which rowed well: hee greatly doubted the well-fare of his father, and the king ſtood in doubt of his ſonne. At his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to his father aboard our ſhip in the Generals ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin, he kiſſed his fathers right foot, &amp; he kiſſed his head
<pb facs="tcp:12277:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Generall had giuen warning to all his company that they ſhould tell no newes of the <hi>Hollands</hi> fleet, but before night it was tould the King and all the reſt, but by whome could neuer be learned. From the twentie two, to the twentie foure, the King and all his crewe taried a bord of vs. the foure and twenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth day, we came by the chiefe towne of <hi>Tarnata,</hi> and ſaluted them with ſeauen peeces of ordinance, the ſame after noone wee came to an anker in the rode, which is in the Southeſt part of the Iland in fourteene fadomes ſandy grownd: the rode is from the towne two leagues and a halfe. The twentie fiue day the king ſent for his plate and vittells from the towne, and feaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the Generall in his owne cabin, there ſat none of his nobles with him at table, none ſat but his ſonne and the Generall: the reſt ſat vpon the floore of the Cabin croſſe legged, like tailors: after dinner the Generall deſired him that he would take ſome order, he might haue a houſe to eſtabliſh a factorie, for that he was minded to goe to the <hi>Portugals</hi> to ſee what he could do with them: the King perſwaded him earneſtly not to meddle with them, for he was ſure there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but villanie and trecherie with them: The Generall ſayd it was a folly to diſſwade him from it, and therefore prayed him that he might haue a houſe ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his promiſe. The King ſeeing in what ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtnes the Generall did ſpeake vnto him, ſayd hee would preſently depart to the town, and cauſe a houſe to be prouided in a redineſſe for his Marchants. The twentie ſix before day our Generall was in a redines with ſuch Marchants and Marchandizes as he minded to leaue at <hi>Tarnata,</hi> went to the towne, and an howre
<pb facs="tcp:12277:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>before day came thirther, the King hearing a noyſe of trumpets knew that our Generall was come, and ſent a ſmall <hi>Prawe</hi> to our pinnes to will our Generall to come vnto him; he was a board the admirall of the <hi>Caracoles,</hi> he came into our pinnes and ſat ſome halfe an howre there taking <hi>Tabacko,</hi> and then came the <hi>Saben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor,</hi> with light and brought the Generall to his houſe, and the King to his <hi>Caracole.</hi> Our Generall preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his landing cauſed his men to land all our goods, &amp; carrie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the houſe, which was performed before day light: then the <hi>Dutch Marchants</hi> enuited the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and Maiſter <hi>Browne</hi> to dine with them, with whome they preſently went to the <hi>Dutch-houſe,</hi> where they ſhewed them, what euery ſort of commodities were worth in that place, with proffers of any kindnes they could doe him. As for the prices of our wares the <hi>Generall</hi> had made enquirie of the <hi>Guſorates</hi> which came aboard, which did agree with the <hi>Dutchmen,</hi> in rating of euery ſort of them, whereby he knewe that they did not diſſemble.</p>
            <p>Before it was dinner time, there came a Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger from the King, to will the Dutch Marchants to come and ſpeake with him; and the Generall came home to our houſe, where hee had not ſtayed halfe an houre, but one of the Dutch Marchants came for him to come ſpeake with the King; So the Generall taking Maſter <hi>Browne,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Addeyes;</hi> one that had the language, and my ſelfe with him, went preſently with them that were preſent, where wee found the King in a large roome ſitting in a chaire, and all his chief Counſellars about him ſitting vpon mattes on the
<pb facs="tcp:12277:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>ground; before him the Dutch-Marchants ſitting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monge them; when the Generall came, the King willed him to ſit downe, after hee was ſet, the King cauſed the Letter brought by our Generall from the kinges Maieſtie of <hi>England</hi> to bee openly read; which being done, the King acknowledged himſelfe behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto his Maieſtie, for ſo kinde a Letter and a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, which he would endeuour to requite. And for confermation thereof, he gaue his ſubiects free leaue to trade with vs for cloues, and likewiſe as one wiſhing vs all the good he could, hee deſired our Generall for his owne good, that he would not haue any thing to doe with his enemies, (the King of <hi>Tidore</hi> and the <hi>Portugalles,</hi>) with whome he ſhould finde no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but treaſon and trecherie.</p>
            <p>The Generall by his interpretor gaue him great thanks for his kindnes, in giuing ſo free liberty to trade with his people, and likewiſe for his good coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell to ſhun the trecherie of the <hi>Portugalls,</hi> but for his part he doubted no trecherie at all ſhould harme him, for that he did mind to ſtand vpon ſuch a gard as all the ſtrength they had ſhould not offend him, and therefore deſired his highnes to pardon him hee did not follow his counſell, for that hee purpoſed withall ſpeede to goe thither and to offer them peaceable trades, which if they refuſed, hee had the thing he deſired, then had he iuſt cauſe to bee at warres with them, and if they would not accept of peaceable trade, hee minded to ioyne with the <hi>Hollanders</hi> againſt them, when GOD ſhould ſend them thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12277:22" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>This ſpech of the Generall, contented the King and all there preſent ſo that they had no more to ſay, but intreat him, that he did not furniſh them with any of our great ordinance, and to take great care of their trechery: and ſo the counſell broke vp, The Generall taking his leaue of the King and all his nobles, for preſently after dinner, he minded to depart abord: alſo the King promiſed, if the <hi>Portingales</hi> would not trade with vs, he would write his letter to the gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of <hi>Makeau</hi> to deale with vs, for all the cloues in that Ile. And, ſo the Generall and Maiſter <hi>Browne</hi> went to the Duch houſe to dinner: which being done he came home with the Duch marchants in his company. And ſo, taking leaue of them and of vs, departed abord.</p>
            <p>The 27. day in the morning came abord 2. men, ſent by the King of <hi>Tarnat,</hi> with aletter to the gouernor of <hi>Makeau,</hi> to trade with vs. They were ſent by the King to go along with vs thither, for our better vſage. So about 8. a cloke in the morning we weighed, &amp; plyed it all day for the roade of <hi>Tidore:</hi> and about ſunne ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting we came to an anchor, in 32. fadomes ſandy ground, on the weſterne ſide of the Ile faire of, by the ſhore. Coming to an anchor there came a <hi>Caricole</hi> with two ſwift Ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>oas to take vewe of our ſhip. Our General Commanded one to weaffe them with a white flag: and preſently, one of the ſmall <hi>Prawes</hi> came faire by vs, demaunding whence we were. Our Generall cauſed our <hi>Portingall</hi> ſoldiar, to will them to come aboord, for we were Engliſh men and their friends. And ſo there came aboord vs three <hi>Portingales,</hi> which entred in to the gallery, and went into the Generalls cabin: where the Generall told them, his comming
<pb facs="tcp:12277:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>thither, was to ſeeke trade with them as friends, for that the wars betweene our nations was done, and a peace co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded, The Queene of <hi>England</hi> being dead, and the King of <hi>Scots,</hi> King of <hi>England.</hi> They made anſwer, that they knew that the Queene was dead, by way of the <hi>Phillipines,</hi> and to heare of the long deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red peace they were very glad, and for trade with vs they ſaid they could ſay nothing, till that they had made the Captaine acquainted therewith: and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was night, they were deſirous to be gone, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſing the next day morning to returne. So the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> let them depart, and our <hi>Portingall</hi> ſouldier with them, with a letter to the Captaine of the fort, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he did certifie him of the newes of Chriſtiandome, and the cauſe of our comming thither, and ſo they departed.</p>
            <p>The 28. day about 6 a clocke, we weighed, hauing very little wind, &amp; at 8. a clocke came a Carticole, &amp; 2. Prawes fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Portingalls</hi> towne, and in them fiue <hi>Portingalls,</hi> and our aboue named ſouldier: the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall</hi> ſtood in the waſt, and entertained them: our ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier telling the <hi>Generall,</hi> the principal of them was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Thome Detoris</hi> Captaine of a Galeon, and the reſt married men of the towne. Captaine <hi>Detoris</hi> deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red our <hi>Generall</hi> a letter from the captaine of the Fort: the effect was, that he was welcome with all his company, to him and all the reſt of the <hi>Portingalls</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting in that place, and whereas the King of <hi>Tarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi> and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> their enemies, had giuen bad re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of them, ſaying there was nothing but villanie and treaſon to be had at their hands, hee hoped our <hi>Generall</hi> did conceiue better of them, and that their
<pb facs="tcp:12277:23"/>reports were of malice and not of trueth, and no cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to be giuen to the report of their enimies. But ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience ſhould proue them lyars, and themſelues no ſuch bad minded people: and therefore he willed the Generall to haue no doubt of good vſage at their hands, and for trade which he deſired with them, hee would reſolue him thereof the next day: for as yet they had not called a councell concerning that mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, without which councell, he could not doe it, but willed him to haue no doubt thereof. So the generall tooke them downe to his Cabin to breakfaſt, and the Carricole and the botes towed the ſhip to the town<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, being very little wind. About eleuenth a clock we came to an anchor, a little to the northwards of the Fort, and ſaluted the fort and towne, with 7 pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Ordinance: and from the fort anſwered with 3. peeces, and preſently vpon the ſame, in a boat came the Captaine of the fort, called <hi>Petro Alleneris Deb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broo,</hi> and the Captain of the other Galeon called <hi>Fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinando Perrera</hi> de <hi>Sandy:</hi> theſe Galeons that theſe Captaines did belong to, did ride within a league of rockes very neere the ſhoare, with their broad ſides to ſeaward, with Ordinance placed therein to ſhoote at their enemies, which come rowing by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſundry times. The Generall brought the Captaine of the Fort, and the other Captaine downe with the reſt to breakfaſt, the Captaine of the Fort making great haſt to be gone. After many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plements paſſed betweene our General and them, they tooke their leaue and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, promiſing the next day to come looke vpon our commodities, and to agree vpon price for them. About 3. a clocke our Generall ſent his brother a
<pb facs="tcp:12277:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſhoare with preſents to the 3. Captaines, which they very kindly accepted: The Captaine of the Fort returning the <hi>Generall</hi> a fat beefe.</p>
            <p>The 29. day came Captaine <hi>Torris</hi> and other <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingalls</hi> aboard, and the <hi>Generall</hi> cauſed our Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants to bring a note of all ſuch commodities as were in our ſhip, into his Cabin: where he ſhewed e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ſort vnto them, ſetting a price vpon them. Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Torris</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Portingalls,</hi> ſaid they were too deare at ſuch rates, ſaying &amp; ptoteſting they ſold better cheape ſuch like co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and therefore deſired the <hi>Generall</hi> to bee more reaſonable, and then he ſhould haue all the Cloues in the <hi>Iland.</hi> The <hi>Generall</hi> with-drew himſelfe apart, and in writing ſet downe his loweſt prices, how hee would ſell, willing them to go a land and conſider of it, &amp; returne with an anſwer (if they could) that night: ſo they tooke their leaue and went a ſhore.</p>
            <p>The 30. day Captaine <hi>Torris</hi> came aboard, and would haue abatement of each ſort of commodities: which the <hi>General</hi> would not yeeld vnto, telling him, if he would not giue ſuch prices, he wold be gone for <hi>Makeau:</hi> and vpon the ſame preſented the two <hi>Tarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taes</hi> which the King ſent to him for the ſame purpoſe. So he ſeeing nothing would be abated of that price, agreed with the <hi>General,</hi> &amp; appointed his own dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling houſe for our factory, with many kinde proffers, which he faithfully performed.</p>
            <p>The 31. being Eaſter day, Captaine <hi>Torris</hi> with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of the principall men of the towne, dined aboard with our <hi>Generall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Aprill the 1. in the morning the <hi>Generall</hi> ſent his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb facs="tcp:12277:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>&amp; M. <hi>Woodnoth</hi> with marchandiſe a land to Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>Torris</hi> houſe, &amp; within an houre after, the <hi>General</hi> went a land himſelf, where he was viſited by the king, the Captaine of the fort, and all the principall men of the towne, who intertained him moſt kindely. They ſtayed ſome ſmall time with him, and departed all of them. They being gone, the <hi>Generall</hi> beganne to ſet his Marchants a worke, to buy Cloues of the <hi>Portin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galls:</hi> &amp; hauing ſet them in a ready way how to deale with them, he went with Captaine <hi>Torris</hi> to dinner, where there was no lacke of good cheere. After din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner come the high prieſt, to welcome our <hi>Generall,</hi> willing him to haue no doubt of any bad dealing in that place: vpon his ſoule hee would vndertake, that there were not any in the towne that wiſhed him or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his company any harme: with many other com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plements, and ſo departed. Captain <hi>Torris</hi> made offer to the <hi>Generall,</hi> to be his chiefe Factor, and to helpe his brother and M. <hi>Woodnoth</hi> in their buſines, each ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing more to doe then they could well turne them to: and to ſay the trueth, he was ſo carefull in their buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, as if it had bin his own. This day died of the flixe, M. <hi>Mitten</hi> our cooke, and of the flixe <hi>Thomas Halls.</hi> The <hi>Tydoryans</hi> came not aboard to ſell vs any thing: the <hi>Generall</hi> doubted it was long of the <hi>Portingals,</hi> who had put them in ſome needleſſe feare.</p>
            <p>The 6. day the <hi>Generall</hi> ſent his brother to the king of <hi>Tydore</hi> with a preſent, and to diuers of his principal men, deſiring his highneſſe, he would giue his ſubiects leaue to repaire aboard with cloues, and freſh victu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls, and that there was no cauſe of feare why they ſhould abſtaine from ſo doing. The King ſaid, they
<pb facs="tcp:12277:25"/>ſhould haue leaue to bring vs refreſhing a board: But for the cloues his people had, ſhould bee brought to the Engliſh-houſe, otherwiſe the quantity wee ſhould buy, would not be knowne, whereby the King of <hi>Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tingall</hi> might looſe his cuſtome, and preſently vppon the ſame, the King made a Proclamation, willing all his people to repaire to the Engliſh factory, with ſuch Cloues as they had. The Captaine of the Fort, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claiming the like in his towne, there came a flying re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> were in ſight, and vpon the ſame the King ſent out a Caricole to ſea, but ſaw no ſhipping.</p>
            <p>The 9. day the Generall ſent his brother a ſhore a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine vnto the King, with a preſent to deſire his high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to giue his ſubiects leaue to repaire aboard with their Cloues, for that the <hi>Portingalls</hi> would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to repaire to his houſe, but would be ſerued themſelues with the beſt wares, and let his people haue but their leauings. Whereupon the King pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed they ſhould come aboard: which they after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards did.</p>
            <p>The 12. day came newes the <hi>Hollanders</hi> were in ſight, and out went the bloudy colours, at the Fort. The 14, day being Sunday Captaine <hi>Torris</hi> the Kings factor, and diuers other of the principal of the <hi>Portin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gals,</hi> dined with the General. This day the Captain of the Fort, ſent our Generall word, that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> were off, and on <hi>Bachan,</hi> willing the Generall to cauſe his factors to get in his debts that were owing before their comming.</p>
            <p>The 15. day the Generall ſent his brother a ſhore, to gather in ſuch debts as were owing, and likewiſe
<pb facs="tcp:12277:25"/>to buy Cloues, if any came to the houſe to bee ſold: which he performed, buying ſome ſmall quantity, for that moſt in the Iland were in our hands, without it were ſome 80. Bahars which the Kings Factor had, which he could not ſell, becauſe they did belong vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Marchants of <hi>Malaea.</hi> The captaine of the fort gaue commandement to al men, to make preſent pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which they honeſtly performed. The Generall ſent to Captaine <hi>Torris,</hi> to know the cauſe: hee ſent him word, we had bought all they had, without it were, thoſe which were in the factors hands, which could not be ſold.</p>
            <p>The 19. day we prepared for our departure from hence, to go to <hi>Makeau.</hi> The 20. day came a <hi>Portingall</hi> a board with a letter to our Generall, from the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the fort, the effect thereof I could not learne. The King of <hi>Tarnatas</hi> two men, which all this time of our being in this place had tarried aboard, were very earneſt with the Generall for their departure to the Ile of <hi>Makeau,</hi> where they made no doubt but to lade our ſhip with cloues. They began to be merry to ſee vs in ſuch readineſſe to bee gone, for they liued in no ſmall feare of ſome treaſon, to be attempted againſt vs by the <hi>Portingals</hi> and <hi>Tydorians,</hi> in ſo much that all the time of our being here, they were the beſt watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in our ſhip. The Generall ſent his brother to the King, deſiring his highneſſe, he would write his letter to the Gouernour of <hi>Taffaſoa,</hi> to ſell him ſuch cloues as they had there, which he preſently did. This towne of <hi>Taffaſoa</hi> is vpon <hi>Makeau</hi> and holds for the King of <hi>Tydore.</hi> all the reſt of the Iland is the Kings of <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12277:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The 21. day being Sunday, came the ſame <hi>Portin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall</hi> that brought our Generall the letter the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, with commendations from his Captaine to the Generall, &amp; to certifie him the <hi>Hollanders</hi> ſhips were in ſight. The <hi>Portingall</hi> taking his leaue, about eleuen a clocke wee weighed with a ſmal fauourable gale of winde, to go for <hi>Makeau.</hi> As we paſſed by the Fort, we ſaluted the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with 5. peeces, they anſwering vs with 3. Likewiſe comming thwart the Kings towne, we gaue them 5. peeces, and were anſwered with 6. from the <hi>Galcons.</hi> At this preſent we had ſight of the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers.</hi> Capten <hi>Torris</hi> our Generals great friend, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a board preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted him with hens, which be both ſcarſe and deare, and ſo tooke his leaue: we keping on our courſe with little winde, for <hi>Makeau,</hi> paſſing bettwene <hi>Mottera &amp; Poulacaualya,</hi> the <hi>Holla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders</hi> ſeing vs come rome vpon them, were in good hope we had beene a <hi>Portingall</hi> that for feare was flying away. Night being at hand, they ſpread themſelues, that we could not paſſe them, but one or other muſt needes ſee vs. About midnight, we came amongſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding our trompetes, whereby they did know we were not <hi>Portingales.</hi> The Admirall ſent his ſhiper in his pinnaſſe aboord, to know what newes: which was certified them at full. He departing, they ſaluted vs with 3. peeces of ordinance: we anſwred them with the like. They told our Generall, that they had taken <hi>Amboyna</hi> caſtell, and left a garriſon therein.</p>
            <p>The 22. day we came to an anchor about ſeuen a clocke at night, a little to the eaſtwards of the chiefe towne of <hi>Makeau:</hi> the towne is called <hi>Mofficia,</hi> in which towne the <hi>Viceroy</hi> for the King of <hi>Tarrata</hi> is
<pb facs="tcp:12277:26" rendition="simple:additions"/>reſident, this after noone, came a cary cole aboard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we came to an anchor, and told our General, they would go about the Ile, and to all the townes, to giue them warning to repaire to our ſhippe with their cloues before night. They had compaſſed the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and came aboard vs againe.</p>
            <p>The 23. day, the Generall ſent his brother with the two <hi>Tarnataes,</hi> and the Kings letters, and a preſent to the Gouernor. The preſent hee receiued, and cauſed the letter to be publikely read: but for the cloues of that Iland, he ſaid they were not ripe, but thoſe fewe that were to be had, the Generall ſhould haue them the next day. This day died of the flixe, our Baker <hi>Griffith Powell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 24. day the Generall went a ſhore himſelfe, to the Gouernor, to know why the people came not with cloues according to promiſe. He made anſwer, he thought there were not any ripe in the Iland, but he had ſent to all the townes, to warne them to bring in cloues: which they would not faile on the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. The Generall ſeeing their delayes, began to ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect, the King of <hi>Tarnataes</hi> letter was to command them to ſell vs none: therefore, if they came not the next day, he would go to <hi>Taffaſoa.</hi> Much quarrell and war is betweene thoſe of this place, and they of the Iland: and if there bee any taken of either part, the moſt fauour they ſhew them, is to cut off their heads.</p>
            <p>The 25. day came moſt of the chiefe men of the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land aboard to our Generall, and told him they had ſmall ſtore of ripe cloues in the Iland, which they were willing he ſhould haue. But they were ſent for, by the King of <hi>Tarnata,</hi> to repaire with their forces, to
<pb facs="tcp:12277:27"/>aſſiſt him in his warres, againſt the King of <hi>Tydore,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Portingalls:</hi> and therefore deſired him not to bee offended with them, for that that they could not ſell him cloues till the wars were done. This day they of <hi>Taffaſoa</hi> had taken ten men of this towne, and cut off their heads.</p>
            <p>The 26. we weighed, with very little wind, and pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it for <hi>Taffaſoa,</hi> which ſtandeth on the weſt-north<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weſt part of the Iland.</p>
            <p>The 27. day the Generall ſent his brother in his pinnaſſe to the towne of <hi>Taffaſoa</hi> with the king of <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dores</hi> letter, which he deliuered. The gouernor hauing read it, made anſwer, that all the cloues they could make, the General ſhould haue: for that the King had ſent him word in an other letter, which hee receiued the day before, that he ſhould cauſe all in the towne to be ſold him. The <hi>Portingalls</hi> haue a ſmall Block<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe with 3. peeces of Ordinance in this towne, wherein were fiue <hi>Portingalls:</hi> they had ſome cloues which they promiſed the Generall ſhould haue. The pinnaſſe returned, and brought one of the <hi>Portingalls</hi> aboard, the ſhip lying becalmed all the time of their abſence.</p>
            <p>The 28. day, about 10. a clocke in the morning, we came to an anchor, right before the towne of <hi>Taffa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoa</hi> in 70. fadome water, hard by the ſhore.</p>
            <p>The 29. day the Generall went a land to the Gouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, who offered himſelf, &amp; towne, to be at his diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition ſaying his King co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manded him ſo to do. The Generall demanded, whether the people would bring their cloues aboard: he made anſwer, they had ſmall ſtore of boats, and could not therefore ſo conuenient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:12277:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>come aboard. So the Generall told him, he would ſet vp a tent vpon the ſtrand, right againſt the ſhip: if he would cauſe his people to bring them thither, hee liked well thereof and came downe with the General to chooſe out a conuenient place, and ſo tooke his leaue, promiſing, ſo ſoone as the Generall ſent aboard to will them to make prouiſion to ſet vp a tent: which in two houres after was done.</p>
            <p>The 30. day was an alarum in the towne, their eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies hauing taken a man without the walls, &amp; cut off his head. The King of <hi>Tydore</hi> hath ſouldiers there, which keepe good watch and ward, the towne ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpon a point of a land, cloſe by the ſea, and is compaſſed with a wall. The King of <hi>Tarnata</hi> hath twiſe attempted with all his force to take it, but could do no good. They liue in ſuch feare, they dare not at any time go a flight-ſhot out off their walles, without a gard of ſouldiers. They haue often truce, but they breake it vpon ſlight occaſions. A little before night the Gouernor came to our Generall, and told him, there were no more cloues to be had, and therefore he preſently cauſed the tent to be pulled downe, and ſent all things aboard.</p>
            <p>The ſecond day in the morning our General recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued a letter from the Captaine of the fort, wherein he certified him, of the burning of the two Galeons by the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and intreated him to make ſpeed thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſee the fight, which he dayly expected and to bring thoſe fiue <hi>Portingalls</hi> with him, which were at <hi>Taffaſoa:</hi> willing the Generall, that he ſhould come to an anchor before the Kings towne, where hee ſhould haue all the cloues they had.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:12277:28"/>
            <p>The 3. day in the after noone, we came before the Kings towne, where we found all the <hi>Hollanders</hi> ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, and let fall an anchor amongſt them, in a 100. fadomes, fayre by the ſhore. The King of <hi>Tarnata</hi> was likewiſe there, with all his Carricoles. After the moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of our ſhip, the Generall ſent M. <hi>Graue</hi> our Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to the Dutch admirall, who found but cold inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainement: the Dutch affirming, we had aſſiſted the <hi>Portingalls</hi> in the laſt fight, whereby they had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued great hurt, &amp; that they were told ſo by a <hi>Goſſorat.</hi> The Maiſter denied it, and ſaid, the <hi>Goſſorat</hi> lyed like a dogge: ſaying, if the Generall had done ſo, hee would not denye it, for any feare of them, but iuſtifie it to their faces, either here or any where elſe. Theſe hot ſpeeches being ouerpaſſed, they grew into milder termes, and then they began to tell our Maiſter the manner of their fight with the Galeons, and the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of them, with the loſſe of ſome of their men in the ſame fight: and they minded the next day to fall downe to the Fort, and lay battery to it: which they had done before, if the King of <hi>Tarnata</hi> had not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold them, in perſwading them to tarry for more helpe, which he expected fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the other Ilands. So the Maiſter hauing learned what news he could, came a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, and told the Generall, what ſpeeches had paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. An houre after the Maiſters comming aboard, there came a praw from the Kings towne, with a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to our Generall from Captaine <hi>Torris,</hi> wherein there was nothing but commendations, and that hee would come aboard, when it was darke, and ſee him. The General willed him to come, either night or day, he ſhould be welcome. This euening the King of
<pb facs="tcp:12277:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Tarnata</hi> rowed ouer for <hi>Battachina,</hi> with all his Carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coles: &amp; Captain <hi>Torris</hi> came aboard to ſee our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, tarrying ſome two houres, telling the Generall, they deſired to fight with the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> not doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of victory: and for ſuch cloues as they had, they ſhould be brought to the Kings towne, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueied aboard vs. So growing very late, he tooke his leaue and depatted aſhore.</p>
            <p>The 5. day, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> expected the comming of the King of <hi>Tarnata</hi> but he came not.</p>
            <p>The 6. day, our Generall ſent ſent his brother and M. <hi>Woodnoth</hi> to the King of <hi>Tydore,</hi> to know if he wold ſel them any cloues. He made anſwer, at that time all his people were buſie in fortifiyng the towne, ſo that he could not ſpare them from their worke, but bid the Generall aſſure himſelfe of all the cloues that hee and the <hi>Portingals</hi> had. This night came one of our men in a ſmall Carrycole, from <hi>Tarnata,</hi> and told our Generall, that they were hardly vſed by the King of <hi>Tarnata,</hi> in not ſuffering them to buy and ſell with his people, according to promiſe, and had taken their weight from them, giuing commande<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent that no man ſhould ſell them any cloues. Likewiſe he ſaid, that they could get no victualls for their money, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the warres, and that all our men were very ſicke, ſaue M. <hi>Browne.</hi> The king by his Carricole, ſent the <hi>Hollanders</hi> word, he would be with them in the morning.</p>
            <p>The 7. day in the morning came the King of <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata,</hi> with all his forces, and he himſelfe went aboard the <hi>Hollands</hi> admirall, where moſt part of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone was ſpent in counſell, and about one of the
<pb facs="tcp:12277:29" rendition="simple:additions"/>clocke the ſhips weighed, and came vnder their fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>topſailes faire by the Fort, and let flye all their Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, the Fort ſhooting now and then a peece at them. They came to an anchor a little to the North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes of the Fort, where they ſpent the moſt part of that afternoone in ſhooting at it, but harmed them not at all. The <hi>Portingalls</hi> could not harme the ſhipps as they rid, hauing but one peece laid out that way. In the hotteſt of this battery, the King of <hi>Tarnata</hi> &amp; the <hi>Hollanders</hi> landed ſome of their forces a little to the northward of the towne: not finding any reſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance they intrenched themſelues where they lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the ſand, and there continued all the night without moleſtation. After the <hi>Hollanders</hi> had done their battery, Captaine <hi>Torris</hi> came aboard, to ſee our Generall, where he was very merry and pleaſant, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as alwaies he had, that they nothing doubted of a happy victory, and for ſuch Ordinance as had bin ſhot at them, it had done them no harme at all, onely he was ſorry that the Ordinance did hinder them for bringing of cloues to him. But he deſired the General to haue a little patience, &amp; he ſhould not want cloues to lade his ſhip: which were nothing out wordes, for it was well knowne to the Generall hee had but 80. bahars in the towne, which the factor had.</p>
            <p>The 8. day, very early in the morning, the ſhippes beganne to batter the fort. which continued the moſt part of the morning, in which time thoſe men of the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> which lodged a land, had brought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues within Saker ſhotte of the Fort, and there rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a mount, whereon they placed a great peece of Ordinance, and began their batterie. The <hi>Portingals</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12277:29"/>now and and then ſhooting a peece to no purpoſe.</p>
            <p>The 9. day, before it was light, the ſhips beganne their battery, and they likewiſe from the mounte, and vpon a ſodaine the <hi>Dutch,</hi> and the <hi>Tarnataes</hi> ſallied out off their trenches, with ſcaling ladders, and had entred vpon the walles, before the <hi>Portingalls</hi> in the Fort were aware, and had placed their colours vpon their ramparts, which the <hi>Portingalls</hi> ſeeing, came with a charge vpon them, with ſhot and fire-workes, throwing at them which were ſo mounted, that they caſt downe their weapons, and leaped downe far fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter then they came vp, leauing their colours and their furniture behind them: the <hi>Portingalls</hi> ſtill continuing throwing of fire workes amongſt them, whereby di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uets were hurt and ſcalded. At ſuch time as the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> gaue the ſcalado, 30. of the choiſeſt <hi>Portingals</hi> with great number of the <hi>Tydorians</hi> were going in the woodes to giue an aſſault vpon the backes of them which were lodged, where the peece of Ordinance was mounted: in which time of their abſence, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> entred vpon their walles. If theſe men had bin in the fort it had gone far worſe with the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers.</hi> The <hi>Portingalls</hi> that were abroad, hearing the alarum at the fort, came running backe againe, &amp; ſome that ran faſteſt, came to the walls, at ſuch time as they in the Fort had put them to the retreat, where they went to handy blowes with them. Captaine <hi>Tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> which had the leading of the 30. men, was ſhotte with a muſket and ſlaine. By this time the moſt of the 30. <hi>Portingalls</hi> were gotten, ſome within and ſome vnder the walls: and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> and <hi>Tarnatans</hi> throwing away their weapons, beganne to take their
<pb facs="tcp:12277:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>heeles to runne into the ſea. At this very iuſtant, when the <hi>Portingalls</hi> and the <hi>Tydorians</hi> had the victory in their hands, and very ready to charge vpon their fly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enimies, the Fort tooke fire, and blewe vp euen with the ground, ſo that all the <hi>Portingalls</hi> which were vnder the walles of the ſort were there buried, and the moſt part within the Fort were blowne vp into the ayre: The Captaine being newly gone out to place two ſouldiers at a little poſterne dore, gaue them charge to kill any <hi>Portingalls</hi> which ſhould go out that way, in which time of his abſence, the Fort was blowne vp, whereby his life was ſaued but howe, or by what means it tooke fire it could not be known. The <hi>Hollanders</hi> and <hi>Tarnatans</hi> ſeeing the fort blowne vp, began to gather vp their ſcattered weapons, and made a ſtand, not daring to enter the rumes of the Fort, till the <hi>Portingalls</hi> had left it: which was ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fe an houre after. In which time the <hi>Portingall</hi> and <hi>Tydory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> ſlaues had ſacked the towne, ſetting fire on the factory, where the cloues were, which they could not carry with them, leauing nothing of any worth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind them. When the King of <hi>Tarnata</hi> ſaw the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory on his ſide, he with all the Carricoles, came rowing towards the Kings towne, in triumph: but durſt not come very neere, for that the King of <hi>Tydore</hi> did ſhoot at them. And ſo rowing by our ſhip, ſinging and making great mirth, returned to the Fort, where was no reſiſtance, but ſo long as the <hi>Portingalls</hi> had it, he durſt not come within a mile, Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the <hi>Tarnataes</hi> had pillaged the towne, they ſet all the houſes a fire which were quickly burnt euen with the ground, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all made of canes. After this victory, the King of
<pb facs="tcp:12277:30" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>Tidore</hi> ſent his ſonne &amp; a Nobleman, to our General, deſiring him to be a meanes of peace betweene the <hi>Holladers</hi> and him, for now he had what he deſired, which was victorie ouer the <hi>Portingales.</hi> The Generall ſent him word, he would do his beſt, as well for him, as for the <hi>Portingalls,</hi> which by fortune of warre were fallen into their enimies hands. So preſently the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall cauſed the Pinnaſſe to be manned, and he and the Maiſter went aboard the Dutch Admirall. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they came thither, they aſked for the Admirall, who was a ſhore: but they ſent for him. At his comming, he bad our Generall welcome, after many ſpeeches paſſed of their fight, and commendations vndeſerued giuen of themſelues, they exclaimed vpon the <hi>Tarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taes</hi> for cowards and attributed all the glory to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, ſaying they durſt not ſtand by them in the fight, but ran away. After a great deale of vaine glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious commendations of themſelues, the Generall was deſirous to ſee what priſoners they had taken of the <hi>Portingalls:</hi> one was brought forth being one of Captain <hi>Pereros</hi> ſouldiers. The Generall bad him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare a trueth in a matter he would aſke him: he made anſwer if he could he would, then he aſked him what great ordinance, powder, ſhot &amp; guns, they had from him to aſſiſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? He anſwered, he knew not of any, ſo turning to the Dutch admiral, he maruailed he ſhould giue credit to ſuch vntruths reported by a ſlaue. Hee anſwered againe, ſuch things were told, but he did not beleeue them to be true. So the Generall aſked, what he ment to do with the <hi>Portingales</hi> his priſoners? He ſaid he would hang them. The Generall intreated him to ſhew them mercy: conſidering they did no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:12277:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>but what all good ſubiects are bound to doe, in defence of their King and Country: and therefore deſired not to take their liues, nor deliuer them to the King of <hi>Tarnata.</hi> He promiſed, at his intreaty, not any one of them ſhould die, nor be deliuered to the King of <hi>Tarnata,</hi> but that he would ſhip them away to <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nallia.</hi> The General gaue him thankes, taking leaue of them, and came rowing along the ſhore, by the kings towne, where he tooke in the Captain of the Fort, &amp; brought him along with him aboard, where he both ſupped and lodged, and from him had the trueth, of all the fight, farre differing from that which the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> reported. The Generall told him his going to the Dutch Admirall was, principally to intreat him, to ſhew mercy vnto the <hi>Portingales:</hi> which he promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to performe. The Captaine gaue him great thanks for the care he had of them, ſaying, now all their hope reſted vpon him: and vpon the ſame, hee preſented the Generall with a ſmall Ruby ſet in a ring, praying him to weare it for his ſake: which the General would not take, ſaying, what he could doe for them, was in Chriſtian charity, and not for reward.</p>
            <p>The 10 day, in the morning, our Generall went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board the <hi>Hollands</hi> Admirall, to ſee if he could bring the King of <hi>Tarnata</hi> and the King of <hi>Tydore,</hi> and the <hi>Hollanders</hi> to a peace. The Dutch admirall made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, the King of <hi>Tarnata</hi> would bee very hardly drawne to any peace with the King of <hi>Tydore,</hi> but he for his part would be willing thereunto: and if it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the King of <hi>Tydore,</hi> to repaire aboard his ſhip, hee ſhould ſafely come and go, to haue conference with him. The Generall thought, he could perſwade him to
<pb facs="tcp:12277:31" rendition="simple:additions"/>come aboord his owne ſhippe, ſo that he would leaue two duch Captaines a ſhore in pledge for him. But to come aboard his ſhip, he was ſure he would not. So the Dutch Admiral ſent two of his chiefe Marchants with the General, to be left as pledges, if the King would come aboard: whereupon our Generall went to the king of <hi>Tydore,</hi> and told him what he had done in his behalfe, perſwading him to come aboard our ſhippe, which he was loath to yeeld to. The Generall ſeeing him feareful, told him, there was no ſuch cauſe, for that he had brought two Dutch Captaines, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine as pledges, and that he would leaue his brother with them. Then the King was willing, and cauſed his own boate to be fitted, &amp; imbarked himſelfe. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ready to put off, came the Kings ſiſter, and his ſon weeping as if he had gone to death, detayned him in this manner halfe an houre. In the end he put off, but when he was halfe way betweene the ſhore and the ſhip, he ſaw a Carricole rowing off from the Fort: which he ſtood in feare of and would proceed no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but returned backe, promiſing the next daye to come aboard, if we would ride with our ſhip nearer his towne.</p>
            <p>The 11. day, in the morning we weighed, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chored againe before the Kings towne. The General with his pledges going a ſhore, there was an alarum in the town, which was ſodainly done: the cauſe was, that a great number of the <hi>Tarnataes</hi> had conſorted to go robbe ſome out-houſes in the Kings towne, and finding nothing therein ſet them a fire. The <hi>Tydo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> gaue a ſodaine aſſault vpon them, and had the cutting off, of a dozen of their heads: all the reſt hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:12277:32"/>eſcaped by running away. The heads they preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to the King, our Generall ſtanding by him, telling him the cauſe. The King ſeemed to be offended with the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> which had promiſed that no hoſtility of warre, ſhould bee offered in this time of parlye. The <hi>Hollands</hi> Captaines which were in our Pinnaſſe ſeeing the heads, were in no ſmall feare of their owne. After the rumor was appeaſed, the King imbarked himſelfe with our Generall, and the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Fort. The Dutch Marchants, and Captain <hi>Middleton</hi> rowed a ſhore for Pledges, but the King and our Generall came aboard our ſhip, where they ſtayed the comming of the Dutch Admirall: who comming aboard was brought downe to the King, in the Generalls cabbin, and they ſaluted one the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther very friendly. After ſome little pauſe, the King ſaid, whereas at your firſt comming hither you ſent me word, your comming was not to harme mee, nor any of my ſubiects, but to expell the <hi>Portingalls</hi> your enimies out of the land, and make the place open for trade for al nations, and therfore you deſired I ſhould not take with them againſt you: which I performed till ſuch time I did ſee my mortall enimy, the King of <hi>Tarnata</hi> ioyne with you, ſo that I was inforced to arme my ſelfe againſt him, who I know deſireth no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much as the ouerthrowe and ſubuertion of my eſtate, and therefore you haue iuſt cauſe not to blame me for arming my ſelfe and people, againſt the inuaſion of my mottall enimy. And now ſeeing you haue the vpper hand of your enimies the <hi>Portin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>galles,</hi> it reſteth in your power to diſpoſe of them as you ſhall thinke good. Now you haue your deſire
<pb facs="tcp:12277:32" rendition="simple:additions"/>of them, I would know whether you will haue peace, or ioyne with the King of <hi>Tarnata</hi> againſt me. The Dutch Admiral anſwered, his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming was only to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel the <hi>Portingals:</hi> which he tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ked God, was now in his power. And for peace, he ſaid it was the thing he deſired with al princes in thoſe parts, &amp; that he wold doe what in him did lie to make an agreement, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the King of <hi>Tarnata</hi> &amp; him. The King anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that he deſired a good peace, but it could hardly be: for that any ſlight occaſion, was dayly cauſe of breach betweene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therfore he deſired the <hi>Holla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> they wold take part with neither, &amp; he doubted not, he ſhould haue as good as he brought. The Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirall anſwered, he would do what he could, to make an agreement: which if he could not bring to paſſe, he promiſed the King (taking our Generall to witnes) that he would take part with neither of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Which ſpeeches greatly contented the King, who excuſing himſelfe of not being well, tooke leaue and went a ſhore. After the King was gone, came the Captaine of the Fort, looking very heauilie, as he had iuſt cauſe: which the Dutch Admirall ſeeing, tooke him by the hand, bad him bee of good cheere, telling him that it was the chance of war, and that the fury being nowe gone, he minded to deale friendly with him and all the <hi>Portingals:</hi> Willing him to repaire aboard, where he ſhould be welcome, and ſafely go and come. The Captain gaue him thanks, for his kindenes. So dinner being ready, &amp; the pledges come from the ſhore, they dined all with our Generall, &amp; departed euery man to his home. The 12. day being ſunday, the <hi>Portingal</hi> cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain with 6. of the principall of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, came aboard to dine with our General, intreating him to go with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:12277:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>to the Dutch admiral, &amp; be a meanes to haſten their departure, which he did, and at his intreaty they were ſent away in three Pinnaſſes and a frigat, to <hi>Manillia,</hi> for which they gaue the Generall great thankes.</p>
            <p>The 12. day, the Generall ſent his Pinnaſſe to <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata,</hi> with prouiſion of victualls to our men which were there: &amp; they returned the next day, &amp; brought our Generall worde of the death of his ſeruant <hi>Iohn Abell,</hi> for whom he was very ſory.</p>
            <p>This 13. day our Generall and the Maiſter went to the King of <hi>Tornata,</hi> to know whether hee would let him leaue a factory in his Ila<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of <hi>Tarnata?</hi> He anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he ſhould, but willed him to returne the next day, for that he would call a counſell concerning the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and then would giue them an anſwer. Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thence the Generall went aboard the Dutch Admirall, and there told him, how the king of <hi>Tarnata</hi> had promiſed he ſhould haue a factory there: yet neuertheleſſe, if he would buy ſuch wares as we had left, and make pai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment at <hi>Bantam,</hi> he ſhould haue them. Who anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, he thought the King of <hi>Tarnata</hi> would not forget himſelfe ſo much, as to graunt vs a Factory, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring he had written to his excellency, and likewiſe promiſed him, that they would trade with no nation but with them. And as touching our commodityes, he would not deale withall, for that they had two ſhips which were ſent, one to <hi>Bengalla,</hi> and the other to <hi>Cambia,</hi> to buy ſuch co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities, which they dayly expected. Our Generall ſaid, he had no reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to croſſe him, for leauing a factory there, for that Sir <hi>Francis Drake</hi> had trade in <hi>Tarnata,</hi> before the names of the <hi>Hollanders</hi> were knowne in thoſe parts of the world.
<pb facs="tcp:12277:33" rendition="simple:additions"/>So, for that time they parted, either part to take their beſt aduantage for their aduentures. The 14 day, the Generall went againe to the King, to know his anſwer concerning his factory. he found him aboard a Carti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cole &amp; one of the Dutch Captaines in his company. The Generall told him, his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming was according to his appointment. The king made preſent anſwer, he could gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t him no factory, for that he had made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe by writing, and word to the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> that no nation ſhould haue trade with him or his people, but onely they. The Generall demanded, why he had not told him ſo, when he ſaued him from the <hi>Tydorians?</hi> and then he could haue told what to haue done. He ſaid, both he and his ſubiects were willing we ſhould tarry there, But the <hi>Hollanders</hi> did ſtill vrge his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe. The Generall ſeeing he could not leaue a facto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, deſired him to ſend ſuch order to <hi>Tarnata,</hi> that hee might haue leaue to carry thoſe ſmall quantity of cloues as his factors had bought and payed for, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>board, and he would trouble neither him nor the <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers.</hi> The king anſwered, that within ſeauen dayes he would be there himſelfe, deſiring the Generall, to ride ſtill. He made anſwer, he liued at too great char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to lye ſtill, and doe nothing, and therefore could ſtay no longer, but wold be gone the next morning: and ſo departed from him.</p>
            <p>The 19. day, the Generall went a land, and tooke his leaue of the King of <hi>Tydore,</hi> and al his Noble men and all the <hi>Portingals,</hi> they being all ſory for his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture.</p>
            <p>The 20. day, we weighed in the morning, for <hi>Tarnata</hi> and at 5. a clocke in the euening, came to an anchor
<pb facs="tcp:12277:34" rendition="simple:additions"/>againe on the north-eaſt ſide of <hi>Tydore.</hi> This day died of the flixe <hi>Thomas Richmond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 21. day, at 4. of the Clocke in the morning we weighed, and about 10. a clocke, came to an anchor in <hi>Tarnata</hi> rode in 16. Fadomes, fayre by one of the Dutch ſhips, which two dayes before vs came from <hi>Tydore.</hi> this ſhip was to take in her lading of Cloues here. This after noone, the Generall ſent his Pinaſſe, to knowe, if the King had ſent word to the <hi>Sabendor</hi> to ſee the deliuery of ſuch cloues, as was there of ours. The pinnaſſe brought word, M. <hi>Browne</hi> was very ſick, and all the company which were with him. This after noone came aboard to our Generall, the Kings vncle of <hi>Tarnata</hi> called <hi>Cichell Gegogoe.</hi> To this man our ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall told, how vnkindly he had beene vſed by the King and the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and howe the King would neither giue him leaue to buy cloues, whiles he tarri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed here, nor permit him to leaue a factory there, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the promiſe he made him, when hee ſaued both him &amp; the <hi>Hollands</hi> factors, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> enimies hands: which good turne both the one and the other haue quite forgotten: likewiſe he ſaid he thought the king had beene as our Kings in Chriſtiandome are, which neuer will promiſe any thing, but they wil per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it. <hi>Chichell Gegogoe</hi> hearing this, ſaid, he would that night go to the King, and then would tell him how much he did diſhonour himſelfe, to be ſo ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruled by the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> and therfore willed the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall not to haue doubt of leauing a factory, and likewiſe to trade ſo long, as they tarried here in the deſpight of the <hi>Hollanders.</hi> And vppon the ſame, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to be angry, he departed, promiſing the next
<pb facs="tcp:12277:34"/>day to returne againe. This man could ſpeake Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gais, wherby the General let him vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his mind to the full. He knew Sir <hi>Francis Drake,</hi> when he was at <hi>Tarnata,</hi> and had beene aboard his ſhip with him.</p>
            <p>The 22. day, the Generall ſent his brother againe to the towne, to know if the <hi>Sabendor</hi> were come from the King with order to deliuer the cloues. Captaine <hi>Middleton</hi> found him now come to towne, &amp; brought him to our Generall, who told him, he had order to deliuer the cloues, and likewiſe that hee ſhould haue free liberty to buy and ſell aſwell as the <hi>Hollanders:</hi> &amp; that the King deſired the Generall not to depart til he came, which ſhould be ſhortly after the meſſenger. All this friendſhip <hi>Chiche Gegogoe</hi> procured. The <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bendor</hi> and his two ſonnes ſupped and lodged in the Generalls cabin that night.</p>
            <p>The 26. being ſunday, <hi>Chiche Gogogoe</hi> was al after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone with the General in his cabin, where he feaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, in the beſt manner he could, &amp; gaue him a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry faire caliuer ſet with bone &amp; many other things.</p>
            <p>The 28. day, the pinnaſſe went to the towne, to fetch ſuch cloues away as the Marchants ſhould buye. The Generall or his brother, ſtil going or comming in her, at this time it was Captain <hi>Middletons</hi> chance to be in her, &amp; as he and the Marchants were buſie buying &amp; weighing of cloues, in came a <hi>Tarnatan,</hi> &amp; told them, that there was a man that was indebted vnto vs, that had brought a Canoa laden with cloues, to pay his debts, &amp; the <hi>Hollanders</hi> had both carried him and the cloues to their houſe, becauſe the ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was likewiſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Out ran our men with weapons, but ſhe was gone before they came, or elſe if they had not
<pb facs="tcp:12277:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>made the more haſt, they had not carried them away ſo eaſily as they did. The marriners were hired by one of thoſe factors, whoſe head the Generall ſo lately had ſaued, for a Royall of 8. a man, to do this braue exploit, at their comming aboard. They told the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, how the <hi>Holland</hi> factors vſed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which hee tooke very euill.</p>
            <p>The 29. day, the Generall went to the towne with 20. armed men, ſome ſhot, and ſome pikes, and Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berts: and at his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming, he ſent word to the Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, they ſhould reſtore the cloues they had taken away. They told our Generall, that the party had bin in their debt theſe two yeares, and they could not get him to any paiment, &amp; that the King had made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, that no man, that was indebted vnto the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> ſhould ſell him any cloues, yet neuerthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they would not be their owne iudges, but would ſtand to the iudgement of the King, when he ſhould come: &amp; the cloues to remaine in the <hi>Sabendors</hi> ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, till the matter was tried. So the General was pacified, threatning to giue the baſtinado to the factor which was the cauſe: but after that time, he durſt not paſſe by our dores. This breach betwixt vs and the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> cauſed the king to make the more haſte, for that hee doubted we wold go by the eares with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; hauing very few men in the towne, he doubted the worſt, for that the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> are not beloued of the countrye people: the cauſe is, their manyfold diſorder in their their drunkennes, againſt men, but principally againſt the women. The firſt of Iune, about 1. of the clock at night, came a Caracole fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Tydore,</hi> rowing by our ſhip, calling to the watch. The Generall hearing it,
<pb facs="tcp:12277:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>knew it was the King that ſpake, and roſe out off his bed, &amp; ſaluted him by his name: the King did the like to him, &amp; aſked him, how he knew him in the darke. The Generall by his interpretor ſaid, that he knew him by his voice: which cauſed him to laugh. And ſo ſpending ſome little time in talking, he willed our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall to meete him at the towne in the morning. The Generall gaue him 5. peeces of Ordinance at his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture, which he tooke very kindely. They delight much to heare ordinance to go off at pleaſure ſo that they be not at the coſt. When it was day, the General went to the towne, &amp; had not ſtaied in his houſe halfe an houre, but the king came, &amp; ſpent al the forenoone with him. The Generall was deſirous to know of him, whether he ſhould leaue a factory or no. He anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red he could not tell, for that it was to be determined by a counſell: which he had not leaſure to cal as yet, by reaſon of much buſineſſe. He ſaid, the <hi>Hollanders</hi> did threaten him to forſake his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, &amp; to eſtabliſh a factory at <hi>Tydore,</hi> if he did let the <hi>Engliſh</hi> tarry in the country, and eſtabliſh a factory. They ſaying we were theeues, &amp; robbers: and ſo if he did truſt vs, he ſhould finde vs: ſaying that <hi>Holland</hi> was able to ſet out 20. ſhips, for <hi>Englands</hi> one, and that the King of <hi>Holland</hi> was ſtronger by ſea, then all Chriſtiandome beſides: with many vntrueths of their owne people &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries commendations, &amp; the diſparagement of our people and country, and of al other Chriſtian princes. If this frothy nation may haue the trade of the India<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to thmſelues, which is the thing they hope for, their pride &amp; inſolencie wilbe intollerable. The Generall anſwered, what <hi>Hollander</hi> ſo euer hee were that had
<pb facs="tcp:12277:36"/>told his highneſſe ſo, he lied like a traytor: &amp; ſaid, he would iuſtifie it to their faces: and for their country, if the Queenes maieſty of <hi>England</hi> had not pittied their ruine, in ſending her forces to withſtand the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi> their country had bin ouer-run, &amp; they marked in the faces for traitors and ſlaues many yeares ago. And therfore deſired the King, to inquire of a <hi>Spaniſh Renegado,</hi> which was in the towne, &amp; he would cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie him of the trueth. Then the Generall demanded, whether he ſhould haue thoſe Cloues which the <hi>Fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings</hi> had carried away by force. Hee anſwered, we ſhould haue ſo many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as ſhould paie the debt, &amp; the <hi>Holla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders</hi> ſhould haue the reſt: which was in the afternoone performed. The king told our General, that the morrow he muſt returne for <hi>Tidore,</hi> where he muſt ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d 3. or 4. daies, before he could returne. In the meane time he gaue him leaue, to buy &amp; ſell with his people. And at his returne, he ſhould haue an anſwer whether he ſhould leaue a factory or no. The general intreating him, whileſt he tarried in the country, hee would let him haue a houſe to lodge in, where hee might be nere his buſineſſe, and not be forced euery night to go aboard. The king promiſed he ſhould, and ſo tooke his leaue &amp; departed. An houre after he ſent his <hi>Sabendor</hi> to the Generall, who brought him to a faire cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, the king ſending him a faire gilded bed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, &amp; a Turkie carpet to lie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: ſo after that, the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall was not enforced euery night to go aboard, as before time he had done. The 2. day about 8. a clocke at night, came a light prawe of <hi>Tydore</hi> aboard, with a letter to out Generall: the effect was, that the king of <hi>Tydore</hi> found himſelfe agreeued with the <hi>Hollanders,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12277:36" rendition="simple:additions"/>for taking part with the King of <hi>Tarnata</hi> againſt him: &amp; that vpon his ſending away of the <hi>Portingales</hi> they had ſhot into his towne, demanding <hi>Taffaſoa</hi> to be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred to procure his peace. The General anſwered, he thought he needed not feare the <hi>Holla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders,</hi> for that their ſhipping would ſhortly be diſpoſed of, to other places, &amp; that at any time, for that towne (if ſo it need) he might make his peace. With which anſwer they returned, making a bold atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pt, to either come or go, the ſea being full of their enimies. The 5. day the King of <hi>Tarnata,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Hollanders</hi> admirall came fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
               <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata,</hi> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude of our baniſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. The 6. day the king ſent our Generall word, that both hee and the Dutch admirall ſhould come face to face, before him &amp; his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſell, to heare what either could ſay againſt other. The Generall ſent the king word, he had nothing to ſay againſt the Dutch, vnleſſe he withſtood his lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing of a factory there: which if he did, he deſired his highnes, that they might meete face to face, before him, to heare what either could ſay: the king ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t word, it ſhould be ſo. The Dutch admiral came to our gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, to viſit him. Our Generall aſked, whether he came to procure his baniſhment? He anſwered, he was bound to do the beſt he could for his adue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>turers. The Generall told him, the king was minded the next day to know, why we ſhould not haue a factory in the country as wel as they. He ſaid he would chalenge the kings owne writing and promiſe. The 7. day the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall waited, to be ſent for, to the King: but ſeeing no body came, he ſent to know the reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. He ſent word, he was very buſie that day, and could not intend it till the morrow. The Dutch admiral had confere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce with
<pb facs="tcp:12277:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>the King twiſe this day: where belike he had what he deſired, for as ſoone as night came hee departed for <hi>Tydore.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 8. day, the King ſent his ſecretary, and one of the Dutch Marchants vnto him, with a letter ſealed with hard waxe, which ſeale had two letters, an H &amp; a B. which ſtood for <hi>Hance Beerepot,</hi> with a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants marke betweene the letters. This letter they deliuered, and told him, it was the Kings letter to the King of <hi>England.</hi> The Generall would not beleeue, the King would ſend ſo great a Prince as the King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> a letter with ſo little ſtate, and a Marchants ſeale vpon it. They anſwered: and if he doubted thereof, they would cauſe the King to come, and iuſtifie it. The Generall ſaid, he would not otherwiſe beleeue it. So they left the letter and departed. Halfe an houre after, came the King, &amp; a great traine to our Generals chamber, where ſaluting him kindely, they ſat downe vpon a trunck togither. The King ſaid, I ſent you a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſealed by my ſecretary, which you haue receiued, making doubt, it is not ſent by mee, to ſo great a king, &amp; deliuered with ſo little ſtate, &amp; ſealed with a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts ſeale. Now you heard me ſay thus much, I hope you are ſatiſfied: the letter is ſent by me, and none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, therefore prepare your ſelfe to morrow to bee gone. The General neither would, nor durſt deliuer it to the King of <hi>England,</hi> willing him to take it againe, He would not, but departed.</p>
            <p>The 9. <hi>Chichell Gegogoe</hi> the Kings vncle, hearing how the Generall had bin vſed by the king &amp; the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> came to viſit him at his cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, where there paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed much talke betweene the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> concerning the foreſaid
<pb facs="tcp:12277:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>counterfeit letter, intended to haue bin ſent (to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace of the Generall) to the king of <hi>England. Chichell Gegogoe</hi> aſſuring the Generall, that if it lay in his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, he wold procure of the king, that they might leaue a factory there. Moreouer, that at his next returne to him, he ſhould know the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tents of that baſe &amp; ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous letter, inuented by the <hi>Hollanders:</hi> &amp; ſo he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, with promiſe to returne the next day. The people of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding the <hi>Hollanders</hi> had procured our baniſhment, were much offended that the petty prince of <hi>Holland,</hi> and his (whom they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemd but debauſhed dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kards) ſhould be eſteemed before the mighty King of <hi>England,</hi> &amp; his ſubiects. &amp; knowing we were commanded to depart, brought all their commodities ro vs, &amp; none to the <hi>Hollanders.</hi> Whereat they finding themſelues agreeued, cauſed our beame that we weighed cloues with, to be taken away: but it was reſtored againe, by the meanes of <hi>Chichell Gegogoe.</hi> Which the <hi>Hollanders</hi> perceiuing, they ſent to their admiral at <hi>Tydore,</hi> to returne to <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nata:</hi> which he did, threatning the King, that he would leaue him, and eſtabliſh a factory at <hi>Tydore.</hi> Wherevpon the King with the vnwilling conſent of his councell, gaue order for our baniſhment. ſending the <hi>Sabendor</hi> to our Generall, to will him to lingar no longer but to depart aboard.</p>
            <p>The 16. day towards euening, the king of <hi>Tarnata</hi> with a great company of his Nobles, came downe from the towne, landing right againſt our ſhippe, and cauſed a tent to be ſet vp: ſending for our Generall to come a ſhore, which he preſently did. The King cauſed him to ſit downe by him, excuſing himſelfe,
<pb facs="tcp:12277:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>that we left not a factory there, alleaging, that the <hi>Hollanders</hi> inforſt him to the contrary: he and his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects owing them much, which he hoped to pay the next harueſt: &amp; that the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he would take an other order with them: which being done he cauſed a letter to be read by his Secretary openly, the contents whereof follow at the end of the booke. Sealing it vp, he deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered it to the General, intreating him to returne, and he ſhold be welcome. Who anſwered, that it was in vaine for the <hi>Engliſh</hi> to returne thither, ſo long as the <hi>Hollanders</hi> bare rule, holding it a diſparagement to his nation, to giue place to them, being ſo farre their inferiors. This communication ended, by the ſodaine comming of a great many of lights, and in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt, one of his chiefe Noble men, vnder a Canopy: carrying in a platter of gold, couered with a couer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of cloth of gold, the letter which was before ſo publikely read: and the Generall looking earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not knowing what the matter was, the King cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vnto him, willing him to ariſe, and receiue the let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he ſent to the King of <hi>England.</hi> Which he preſently doing, the party which carried it, made lowe obei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance, after their country faſhion, and then deliuered it to the Generall: which he kiſſing receiued, and ſat him downe againe by the King. Giuing him thanks in doing our king &amp; himſelf that right, in deliuering the letter in ſuch ſort as it ought to be. The king anſwered this letter which you haue, is vnſealed, and written in the <hi>Malaya</hi> tongue, to the intent at <hi>Bantam</hi> it might bee interpreted by ſome of your owne people, which haue learned that language. But the other was inuented by the <hi>Hollanders,</hi> to haue done you iniury: telling him in briefe the effect thereof:
<pb facs="tcp:12277:38" rendition="simple:additions"/>excuſing himſelfe that hee had no good thing to ſend the King of <hi>England,</hi> but onely a <hi>Bahar</hi> of Cloues, which he hoped his Maieſtie would accept in good part, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering his contrey yeelds no other thing of worth. Likewiſe hee beſtowed vpon our Generall a <hi>Bahar</hi> of cloues, and cauſed them preſently to be carried to the Boate: which done, hee tooke his leaue, and departed aboord his Caracole. The 17. day, the King of <hi>Tarn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ata</hi> came roing about our ſhip, and diuers of his women with him in a Caracole; the Generall entreating him to come aboord, but he would not. <hi>Chichell Gegegoe</hi> came aboord this afternoone to our General, certifying him that the contents of the Hollanders counterfeit Letter was, that we had ſolde powder, great ordinance, and other munition to the Portugalls. And more, that to their great hurt in the fight, we had aſſiſted them with Gunners, and that was the cauſe we left not a Factory there, hoping the Generall would haue carried and deliuered it to his owne diſgrace: but he ſuſpecting their ſlaunderous trecherie, refuſed it.</p>
            <p>The 18. day the King and his Vncle came aboord in a ſmall Prawe, becauſe he would not haue the Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers which rid by vs to know of his being there, for it was death to them to ſee him vſe our Generall kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: their comming was to take leaue of our Generall, he deſired them to come downe to his Caben, and made them a banquet, whih they kindly did accept, and ſpent moſt part of the day with him, vrging our Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall to returne thither againe, or at the leaſtwiſe to ſend, and he or they ſhould be welcome, doe the Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers what they could, with proteſtation, that both he and all his people were very ſory for his departure,
<pb facs="tcp:12277:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>finding we were good people, and not ſuch as the Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers did report vs to be, which liued only by rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing and ſtealing. During this communication, the Holland ſhip which rid by vs ſhot off three peeces, which the King hearing, ſent to know the cauſe, word was brought, the Hollanders Admirall was come from <hi>Tydore</hi> and gone aboord, which the King hearing, tooke a ſhort farewell of our generall, and went to his caracole: ſhewing euidently his great feare to offend the Hollanders. Before he could put off his boate from the ſide, our ſhip was vnder ſayle: giuing him ſeuen peeces of ordinance, and helde on our way bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene <hi>Tarnata</hi> and <hi>Tydore.</hi> About noone the 21. day we came to an anker at <hi>Taffaſoa:</hi> the Gouernour pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently came to our Generall with a preſent of hennes, and fruite, telling him that he had been at <hi>Tydore,</hi> and the King had giuen him order to ſurrender the towne vnto him, if he came thither againe, and the ſort, pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to diſpoſe thereof as his owne. The Generall gaue him thankes, telling him he had fewe men, but if he had ſo many as he had when he came from <hi>Bantam,</hi> he would leaue ſuch a Garriſon there, as they ſhould doubt neither the Hollanders nor the Tarnatanes: but his weakeneſſe was ſuch, that hee could leaue no men there. He anſwered, he doubted not the keeping of the towne in diſpite of all their enemies: and although he could leaue no me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there, yet had he order by his king to ſurrender his right and title to the King of <hi>England,</hi> to whoſe vſe he would keepe it, deſiring the ſurrender therof might be drawne, and the Generall ſhould haue the originall and he the copie. Which done he cauſed the people to bring thoſe Cloues they had, &amp; ſo tooke
<pb facs="tcp:12277:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>his leaue and departed, we directing our courſe for <hi>Selebis,</hi> where wee had ſuch water as the place affor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, but it was brakiſh, buyng ſome <hi>Cocus</hi> of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple who are like <hi>lauans.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iuly</hi> the 24. we came to anker in <hi>Bantan</hi> road, were Maſter <hi>Scot</hi> chiefe factor there, certified our Generall of the mortallitie of men in the <hi>Hector,</hi> and <hi>Aſcenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> before they departed, ſo that he was forced to hyer <hi>Chineſes</hi> to helpe them home, and that of 24 left there in their factorie, 12. were dead, where we continued till the ſixt of <hi>October:</hi> which day hauing taken leaue of M. <hi>Scot,</hi> and the reſt left there, we ſet ſaile for <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> continuing in our courſe with variable weather till the 19. of <hi>December,</hi> which day the winde ſcanting vpon vs we though to put into <hi>Saldania</hi> roade: about 10. a clock in the morning we ſaw a ſayle to leewards, thinking it had been the <hi>Aſcention,</hi> whoſe company we loſt 14. dayes before, but contrary to our expectation it prooued the <hi>Hector,</hi> which went in company of the <hi>Suſan</hi> from <hi>Bantam</hi> aboue 9. months before, in ſuch la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable diſtreſſe, that had we not met with them that day, they had purpoſed the next to haue run the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues aground at <hi>Pengwin</hi> Iland, hauing for that purpoſe fard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led vp their apparrel, &amp; ſuch other things as were moſt neceſſary for them. Our General cauſed our Pinneſſe to be hoyſted out and ſent for Cap: <hi>Keeling</hi> &amp; the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer who related their extreme miſeries, hauing but 10. <hi>Engliſhmen</hi> and 4 <hi>Chineſes</hi> aliue: ſo ſupper being done, with thankes giuen to God for their miraculous pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation, our General ſent 12. men more to help the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ldania</hi> road, where we ſtayed repairing the ruines of the <hi>Hector,</hi> &amp; prouiding other neceſſaries til the 16.
<pb facs="tcp:12277:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12277:40" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:12277:41" rendition="simple:additions"/>of <hi>Ianuary</hi> following, when we ſet ſayle for Saint <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena,</hi> where wee ariued the ſecond of <hi>February</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing: the eleuenth of<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>February</hi> we departed from Saint <hi>Helena</hi> continuing at Sea with ſuch varytie of weather, as thoſe that vſe the ſea are vſually accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med vnto, till the ſecond of May following when we were of <hi>Plymoth:</hi> and the ſixt follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at the <hi>Downes.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:12277:41"/>
            <head>The King of <hi>Tarnata,</hi> to the King of <hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and IRELAND, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Earing of the good report of your Maieſtie, by the comming of the great Captain <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Drake,</hi> in the time of my father, which was about ſome 30. yeeres paſt: by the which Captaine, my Predeceſſor did ſend a Ring vnto the Queene of <hi>England,</hi> as a token of remembrance betweene Vs: which if the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide <hi>Drake</hi> had beene liuing, hee could haue informed your Maieſtie of the great loue and friendſhip of either ſide: he in the behalfe of the Queene: my Father for him and his Succeſſors. Since which time of the departure of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Captaine, we haue dayly expected his returne, my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther liuing many yeeres after and dayly expecting his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, and I after the death of my father haue liued in the ſame hope, till I was father of eleuen-children: in which time I haue beene informed that the Engliſh were men of ſo bad diſpoſition that they came not as peaceable Merchants, but to diſpoſſeſſe them of there Countrey: which by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of the bearer hereof wee haue found to the contrarie, which greatly we reioyce at. And after many yeeres of our expectation of ſome Engliſh forces by the promiſe of Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine <hi>Drake;</hi> Here arriued certaine ſhips which we well ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped had beene Engliſhmen, but finding them contrary, and being out of al hope of ſuccour of the Engliſh Nation, we were inforced to write to the Prince of <hi>Holland,</hi> to craue ayde and ſuccour againſt our auncient enemies the <hi>Portingals,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:12277:42"/>and according to our requeſt hee hath ſent hither his forces which hath expeld all the Portugales out of the fortes which they held at <hi>Amboyna</hi> and <hi>Tydore.</hi> And whereas your Maieſtie hath ſent to me a moſt kinde and friendly Letter by your ſeruant Captaine <hi>Henry Middleton,</hi> that doth not a litle reioyce vs.</p>
            <p>And whereas Captaine <hi>Henry Middelton</hi> was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to leaue a factory heare, we were very willing therunto, which the Captain of the Hollanders vnderſtanding, became to challenge me of a former promiſe which I had written to the Prince of <hi>Holland:</hi> that if he would ſend me ſuch ſuccour as ſhould expell the Portugales out of theſe parts, that no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nation ſhould haue trade heare but they onely. So that we were inforſt against our liking to yeeld vnto the Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders Captaines requeſt for this time: whereof we craue par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of your Highneſſe: and if any of your Nation come here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, they ſhall be welcome. And whereas the chiefe Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the Hollanders doth ſollicite vs, not to hold any friendſhip with your Nation, nor to giue eare to your High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe Letters: yet for all their ſuite, if you pleaſe to ſend hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againe, you ſhall be welcome. And in token of our friendſhip, which we deſire of your Maieſtie, we haue ſent you a ſmall remembrance of a <hi>Bahar</hi> of Cloues, our Countrey be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poore, and yeelding no better commoditie, which we pray your Highneſſe to accept in good part.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>TARNATA.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:12277:42"/>
            <head>The King of <hi>Tydors</hi> Letter to the KINGS MAIESTIE OF ENGLAND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HIS Writing of the King of <hi>Tydor</hi> to the King of <hi>England,</hi> is to let your Highneſſe vnderſtand that the King of <hi>Holland</hi> hath ſent hither into theſe partes a Fleet of ſhippes to ioyne with our ancient enemie the King of <hi>Tarnata,</hi> and they ioynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly together, haue ouer-runne and ſpoyled part of our Countrey, and are determined to deſtroy both vs and our Subiects. Nowe vnderſtanding by the bearer hereof, Captaine <hi>Henry Midale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton,</hi> that your Highneſſe is in frienſhip with the King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> Wee deſire your MAIESTIE that you would take pittie of Vs, that wee may not be deſtroyed by the King of <hi>Holland</hi> and <hi>Tarnata</hi> to whom wee haue offered no wrong: but they by forceable meanes ſeeke to bereaue Vs of our Kingdome. And as great Kings vpon the earth are ordayned by God to ſuccour all them that be wrongfully oppreſſed: ſo I appeale vnto your MAIESTIE, for ſuccour againſt my enemies; not doubting but to finde reliefe at your MAIESTIES hands. And if your MAIESTIE ſend hither, I humbly entreate that it may bee Captaine <hi>Henry Middleton</hi> or his Brother, with whom I am well acquainted.</p>
            <p>Thus We end, praying God to enlarge your Kingdomes, and bleſſe You, and all your Counſels.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>TYDOLR.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:12277:43"/>
            <head>The King of <hi>Bantam,</hi> to the King of ENGLAND.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> LETTER giuen from your friend the king of <hi>Bantam,</hi> to the King of <hi>England, Scotland, France,</hi> and <hi>Ireland:</hi> deſiring GOD to preſerue your health, and to exalt you more and more, and all your Counſell. And whereas your MAIESTIE hath ſent a Generall, <hi>Henry Middleton,</hi> he came to me in health. I did heare that your MAIESTIE was come to the Crowne of <hi>England,</hi> which doth greatly reioyce my heart. Now <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Bantam</hi> are both as one. I haue alſo receiued a Preſent from your MAIESTIE: the which I giue you many thankes for your kindneſſe. Idoe ſend your MAIESTIE two <hi>Beaſar ſtones,</hi> the one waying fourteene <hi>Maſſes</hi> the other three: And ſo GOD haue you in his keeping.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Bantam</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12277:43"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
